<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="APRS000020060411e24b002b4" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060411"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Primitive Gaza rockets are stumping Israel's mighty military  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>JERUSALEM (AP) - Crude scrap metal rockets welded in Gaza's backyards have been stumping Israel's mighty military.  </Para><Para>Israel has pounded crowded Gaza with some 2,200 artillery shells in the past 11 days, killing three Palestinian bystanders and wounding 25, but has failed to stop the Palestinian projectiles from reaching Israeli border villages.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Military analysts believe the Israeli barrage, which began after the Islamic militant group Hamas assumed power two weeks ago, is largely driven by the army's frustration and has no direct military purpose.  </Para><Para>The army that vanquished Israel's neighbors in just six days in 1967, repulsed a surprise two-pronged invasion in 1973 and mounted a heroic rescue of hostages from a hijacked plane in faraway Uganda in 1976 has found itself impotent against the Palestinians' primitive tubes filled with simple fuel and a topped with a tiny explosive warhead.  </Para><Para>However, the military said it cannot let attacks on Israeli civilians pass without a response; 32 rockets from Gaza have landed in Israel since the beginning of April, causing no casualties but great anxiety in Israeli border communities. Militants have taken to launching the rockets from populated areas, hoping to avoid being targeted by the Israelis.  </Para><Para>Reserve officers in the artillery said the idea behind the massive shelling is to pressure Palestinian civilians, in hopes that they will eventually chase rocket-launching militants off their property. Israel tried the same tactic in the past, with little success, in years of fighting with the Shiite Muslim guerrilla group Hezbollah in Lebanon.  </Para><Para>The firing across the Gaza-Israel border is fraught with risk on both sides.  </Para><Para>If Israeli civilians are killed by Palestinian rocket fire, Israel might reluctantly reoccupy parts of Gaza. If the death toll on the Palestinian side keeps rising, Israel might come under growing international pressure to stop the shelling.  </Para><Para>Monday's killing of an 8-year-old Palestinian girl by artillery fire also ignited a debate within Israel. The girl, Hadil Ghaben, was in her family home in the northern Gaza town of Beit Lahiya when it was hit by two shells, killing her and wounding her mother and seven siblings. Photos of frantic relatives carrying two little girls with dusty blood-smeared faces appeared in newspapers in Israel and around the world.  </Para><Para>"It is not easy to know what to do, but it is fairly easy to know what must not be done," read an op-ed piece in Israel's Yediot Ahronot daily Tuesday. "We must not take innocent people as hostages, and we must not punish them for the crimes of others."  </Para><Para>After Palestinian militants fired the first Qassam rockets in 2002, the Israeli military used much of its arsenal to try to stop the rockets -- from air strikes against metal workshops and rocket squads to ground incursions and tank fire. The army said the rockets have killed 15 Israelis, eight in Israeli villages and seven in Gaza's Jewish settlements before they were evacuated last summer.  </Para><Para>The Qassams confounded Israel with their simplicity. Their erratic flight path and short range -- they fly just 15-20 seconds -- makes them difficult to intercept, said Shalom Levy, a retired artillery colonel.  </Para><Para>"From the military point of view, it is impossible" to stop the rockets, said Israeli military analyst Reuven Pedatzur. "It is in the air too short a time, it's too small a target, and it's too expensive a system to shoot them down."  </Para><Para>With Israel's withdrawal from Gaza in the summer of 2005, Israel vowed it would not tolerate rocket attacks and would strike back hard. However, the militants have not been not deterred by air strikes or artillery fire.  </Para><Para>After Hamas took power, the army's shelling intensified and troops were given permission to aim at targets just 100 meters (yards) from houses, one-third the previous safety distance of 300 meters, the Haaretz daily reported.  </Para><Para>Since then, three Palestinian bystanders have been killed and 12 houses damaged by the shelling. Hardest hit is northern Gaza, where some 40,000 Palestinians live in the towns of Beit Hanoun and Beit Lahiya close to Israel.  </Para><Para>Hadil's uncle, Alaa Ghaben, said that when shells began landing Monday on the outskirts of Beit Lahiya, he called his clan's children to seek shelter indoors. He said his sister Saffiyeh, 38, and her eight children, were in the house next door. "I heard a huge scream," he said Tuesday. "A big cloud of dust was coming from the house (next door) and the smell of explosives was everywhere." He said he found his niece buried under cement blocks. She died later in the hospital.  </Para><Para>Azzam Omar, a Beit Lahiya farmer, said he blamed the Israeli army and the militants equally. "Everything is like hell," he said. "We are even afraid to sit in our homes sometimes."  </Para><Para>Most of the rockets are being fired by Islamic Jihad and the Al Aqsa Martyrs' Brigades, a violent offshoot of Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas' Fatah Party. Hamas, which took a lead in the development of Qassams, has largely stayed on the sidelines, apparently because it does not want to compound its problems. The new Hamas government faces an economic boycott by the West Bank and has said its coffers are empty.  </Para><Para>Israel said militants are cynically using civilians as human shields by firing from populated areas. "They are doing so deliberately in order to try and draw the Israel Defense Forces into responding into heavily populated areas," said Lt. Col. David Benjamin of the army's international legal department.  </Para><Para>Sari Shanan, an Israeli artillery colonel in the reserves, acknowledged that Israel cannot stop the rockets by military means, but said Israel must maintain its deterrence. "Israel cannot stand by quietly when Qassams are fired, after it has returned to the 1967 borders," he said, referring to the Gaza pullout.  </Para><Para>------  </Para><Para>AP reporter Ibrahim Barzak contributed to this report from Beit Lahiya.  </Para><Para>kl-ml  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>By KARIN LAUB  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'>Associated Press Writer  </Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>7  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006.  The Associated Press.  All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>