<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="APRS000020060411e24b002p7" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060411"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Hamas seeks grass-roots support in Islamic world to wrest additional Arab aid  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>RAMALLAH, West Bank (AP) - Fed up with unmet promises of aid, the Palestinian Authority's new Hamas rulers are organizing protests across the Arab and Islamic world to pressure governments there to send money to the cash-starved Palestinian Authority, a Hamas leader said Tuesday.  </Para><Para>Hamas' refusal to renounce its violent, anti-Israel ideology after its victory in Palestinian parliamentary elections in January has led Israel and the West to withhold hundreds of millions of dollars from a government they view as terrorist.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Palestinian coffers are empty, and unrest in the already volatile West Bank and Gaza Strip is liable to grow because of the government's inability to pay salaries to government employees.  </Para><Para>Hamas initially boasted that it would make up the shortfall by appealing to the Arab and Muslim world. But the Arab states haven't sent fat checks to buttress their rhetorical solidarity with the Palestinians, so Hamas is now pinning its hopes on grass-roots support to bring the money in.  </Para><Para>"In the next few weeks, the world will see demonstrations all over the Arab and Islamic states to pressure the governments to open their treasuries to the Palestinian people," said Farhat Assad, a Hamas leader in the West Bank.  </Para><Para>"Don't forget that Hamas has broad support in the Arab and Islamic world, and that is something Western governments apparently have not realized," Assad said in Ramallah, where hundreds of Hamas supporters gathered to protest what they regard as an unjust financial siege.  </Para><Para>He said the protests were being organized in coordination with Islamic movements throughout the Arab world.  </Para><Para>A delegation of Hamas members of parliament left for Iran this week, but so far Teheran has not chipped in.  </Para><Para>Arab League official Mohammad Sobeih said no new funds have been sent to the Palestinians since the new government took office, though some nations are paying off previous pledges. He said Algeria sent $37 million (euro31 million) to Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas, bypassing the Hamas-led government.  </Para><Para>Analysts say Arab states are reluctant to pour money into the Palestinian Authority because they feel threatened by the Islamic militant group's ascent to power -- and because they're being pressured by Washington not to help Hamas unless it recognizes Israel.  </Para><Para>They see Hamas as part of a global Islamic movement that is challenging autocratic Arab regimes across the region. Experts say Arab governments, afraid that a Hamas victory could have a snowball effect, have no interest in seeing the group succeed.  </Para><Para>"You're talking about a democratically elected Islamic government that is part of the wider Muslim Brotherhood network in the region," said Mouin Rabbani of the International Crisis Group in Amman, Jordan.  </Para><Para>"If that experiment succeeds, then the other parts of the Muslim Brotherhood will be clamoring for elections themselves and feel emboldened to achieve power and leadership through the ballot box," Rabbani said.  </Para><Para>Fear of Islamic power is something that unites countries as disparate as Egypt, Syria and Saudi Arabia, which want to keep Islam in the mosque and not in politics, the analysts added.  </Para><Para>The reluctance of Arab countries like Saudi Arabia, Egypt and Kuwait to cross swords with the U.S. is another reason for Arab stinginess.  </Para><Para>"They're definitely looking at Washington," said Bruce Maddy-Weitzman, a senior research fellow in Middle Eastern studies at Tel Aviv University. "They don't want to be seen as overly supportive of the Hamas government."  </Para><Para>A Jordan-based Arab diplomat, citing signals sent by Washington, said he doubted that oil-rich Gulf Arab states, particularly Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, would step in to make up for the shortfall of Western aid.  </Para><Para>The official spoke on condition of anonymity because he was not authorized to discuss Arab contributions to the Palestinians with the media. He said the Arab world was also keeping its purse strings tied tight because it hoped to see the Hamas-led government make peace overtures to Israel.  </Para><Para>Egypt toed the U.S. line this week when Egyptian Foreign Minister Ahmed Aboul Gheit declined to meet with his Palestinian counterpart, Mahmoud Zahar of Hamas, in Cairo, saying his schedule was too packed.  </Para><Para>Even Iran, the would-be sponsor of a global Islamic revolution, is aware of Washington's "clear messages," Rabbani said.  </Para><Para>"Iran has problems of its own," Rabbani said of the regime in Tehran, which is engaged in a standoff with the West over the Iranian nuclear program. "I don't think it's going to go out of its way to create an additional one."  </Para><Para>Even before Hamas rose to power, Arab states had a history of shortchanging the Palestinian Authority.  </Para><Para>In 2002, the members of the Arab League promised to donate $55 million (euro46 million) a month to the Palestinian Authority. But since 2003, Arab countries have paid out just $761 million (euro628 million) -- just 30 percent of the promised amount over that period. And at the last Arab summit in March, pledges didn't increase, despite the Palestinian Authority's dire financial situation.  </Para><Para>The late Yasser Arafat's tilt toward former Iraqi dictator Saddam Hussein before the 1991 Gulf War, and decades-old Palestinian attempts to topple the regimes in Jordan and Lebanon when living there in exile created bad blood with the Arab world, analysts said.  </Para><Para>Arab states "would like to see a Palestinian state, but the history of relations is mixed," said Shimon Shamir, a former Israeli ambassador to Egypt and Jordan.  </Para><Para>(at/ml)  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>By MOHAMMED DARAGHMEH and AMY TEIBEL  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'>Associated Press Writer  </Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>7  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006.  The Associated Press.  All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>