<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="APRS000020060411e24b0032l" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060411"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Politicians: Foiling attempt to kill Hezbollah leader spares Lebanon Iraq-style sectarian strife  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) - An alleged plot to assassinate the leader of the Shiite Muslim Hezbollah guerrilla group aims to plunge Lebanon into an Iraq-style sectarian strife between Sunnis and Shiites, Lebanese politicians said Tuesday.  </Para><Para>While reacting with shock and dismay to the alleged plot against Hezbollah leader Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, politicians on both sides of the sectarian fence also expressed satisfaction with the capture by Lebanese authorities of members of a gang that planned to carry out terrorist acts.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Lebanon's top military magistrate Tuesday formally charged and issued arrest warrants against nine people for plotting to carry out terror attacks, including the possible assassination of Nasrallah.  </Para><Para>Based on the suspects' preliminary testimonies to a military prosecutor, military magistrate Rashid Mezher charged the nine with "establishing a gang to carry out terrorist acts, undermining the state's authority and trading in and transporting military arms and explosives."  </Para><Para>Mezher told The Associated Press by phone that he will question the nine -- eight Lebanese and a Palestinian -- on Thursday. He added six other members of the ring were still at large.  </Para><Para>Officials have not said if a country or organization is believed to be behind the cell.  </Para><Para>On Monday, a senior Lebanese military official said the plot against Nasrallah was "in the phase of intentions" and had not reached "the phase of implementation."  </Para><Para>The reported plot to kill one of Lebanon's top Shiite clerics and politicians by rockets came as fears of sectarian strife between Shiites and Sunnis have rippled through the Middle East.  </Para><Para>Both Nasrallah and the main political leader of Lebanon's Sunnis, Saad Hariri, son of slain former Premier Rafik Hariri, have pledged not to allow any attempt to foment Sunni-Shiite strife.  </Para><Para>Lebanese Health Minister Mohammed Jawad Khalife warned that the cycle of violence in Iraq might spread to other countries in the region.  </Para><Para>Foiling this "terrible conspiracy ... spared the country disasters with no limits," said former Prime Minister Salim Hoss, a moderate Sunni politician.  </Para><Para>Referring to the sectarian violence in Iraq, Hoss said, "All (Lebanese) are concerned that there are some (people) in Lebanon who want to spread the (Iraqi) contagion to our country."  </Para><Para>"God still loves Lebanon," Christian leader Gen. Michel Aoun said on the arrests.  </Para><Para>Hezbollah, which the United States and Israel brand as a terrorist group, is a major political force in Lebanon with 11 legislators in the 128-seat Lebanese Parliament and two ministers in the 24-member Cabinet. The group credits itself with liberating south Lebanon from Israeli troops in 2000.  </Para><Para>hd-sfg/lk  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>By HUSSEIN DAKROUB  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'>Associated Press Writer  </Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>7  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006.  The Associated Press.  All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>