<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060406e2470000m" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060407"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>OPED</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>One small step for the U.S., one giant leap for Lebanon's sovereignty  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- Editorial  </Para><Para>Since assuming the helm at the U.S. State Department, Condoleezza Rice has shown considerable interest in Lebanon, a country whose sovereignty she has many times defended. On Tuesday, Rice told a U.S. congressional committee that Lebanon's biggest problem now is Hizbullah and its ties with Syria and Iran. While defending U.S. plans to finance democracy-promotion operations in Iran, Rice cited the Islamic Republic's backing of Hizbullah as an example of Tehran's interference in another country's sovereign affairs.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Rice's expressed concern for Lebanon's sovereignty is welcome. But while the secretary is accurate to point out that both Iran and Syria have meddled in Lebanese affairs, she neglected to mention a third party, whose interference in Lebanon has been far more deadly and costly to the Lebanese. That third party, whose ongoing violations of Lebanese sovereignty U.S. officials have failed to criticize, is Israel.  </Para><Para>Indeed it can be argued that Hizbullah, more than being a product of Iranian or Syrian interference, is Israel's own creation. The resistance movement was born out Israel's deadly invasion and even deadlier 22-year occupation of Lebanon. Hizbullah's legitimacy as a resistance movement is currently buttressed by the fact that Israel's occupation and incursions have not yet ended. Israeli troops still patrol the Shebaa Farms and Israeli warplanes still violate Lebanese airspace on nearly a daily basis. As long as Israel has free license to occupy and invade Lebanese territory, the Lebanese resistance remains justifiable.  </Para><Para>If U.S. officials really wanted to protect Lebanon's sovereignty, they would defend the Lebanese against unnecessary Israeli aggression. The Lebanese, and even this newspaper, have repeatedly called upon the U.S. to create a diplomatic barrier for the Lebanese in the face of Israeli aggression by urging the Jewish state to halt its illegal and provocative incursions. Israel has won U.S. support for its separation barrier, a 670-kilometer wall of concrete and razor wire that has created considerable hardships for the Palestinians. The Lebanese are not asking for any concrete or barbed wire; rather, they want just a word - even a whisper - of condemnation against Israel's incursions. Such a simple gesture would be a welcome as a genuine show of support for Lebanon's sovereignty.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Daily Star Staff  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>