<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060404e24500009" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060405"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>POLITICS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Israelis say Iran has set up 'front line' in South Lebanon  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- Iran has set up a sophisticated intelligence-gathering operation in South Lebanon to identify targets in northern Israel in the event of a military confrontation over its controversial nuclear program, The Daily Telegraph quoted Israeli military officials as saying.  </Para><Para>Senior Israeli military commanders say Iran has spent tens of millions of dollars helping Hizbullah to establish a network of control towers and monitoring stations along Israel's border with southern Lebanon, according to the UK-based daily.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Hizbullah refused to comment on the statement.  </Para><Para>The newspaper said that some of the new control towers are made of reinforced concrete and fitted with bullet-proof reflective glass, adding that they are less than 100 yards from Israeli army positions.  </Para><Para>"This is now Iran's front line with Israel," a senior Israeli military commander was quoted as saying. "The Iranians are using Hizbullah to spy on us so that they can collect information for future attacks. And there is very little we can do about it."  </Para><Para>Such comments come as anti-Syrian Lebanese politicians have launched a campaign accusing the Shiite group of serving Syrian and Iranian interests in the region.  </Para><Para>The Israeli army commanders told the Telegraph that Hizbullah has increased its activity in southern Lebanon since Syria came under intense international pressure to withdraw its forces from Lebanon last year following the assassination of former Prime Minister Rafik Hariri.  </Para><Para>Israeli military officers claimed that teams of Iran's Revolutionary Guards travel regularly to southern Lebanon to help train local Hizbullah fighters in what they called "terrorist" tactics. They did not say, however, how they obtained such information.  </Para><Para>Senior Israeli military officers believe Iran is deliberately exploiting the power vacuum caused by Syria's withdrawal to intensify pressure on Israel's northern border.  </Para><Para>The right-wing daily reported that many senior Israeli officers have openly admitted to missing the restraining influence of Syria over Hizbullah.  </Para><Para>"When the Syrians were in Lebanon it was easy for us to control Hizbullah," said an officer with Israel's northern command. "If things got too tense we could put pressure on Damascus and the Syrians would act quickly to calm things down.  </Para><Para>"Iran is playing a very dangerous game of cat-and-mouse on our northern border and it could easily spiral out of control at any moment," the officer told the British newspaper.  </Para><Para>Meanwhile, Israel may soon be facing international pressure to withdraw from the Shebaa Farms region on its northern border in light of the possibility of the area being declared Lebanese territory, Israeli officials estimate.  </Para><Para>According to Yediot Aharonot, other sources in Israel believe the scheme would not materialize because the chances of Syria agreeing to it are slim.  </Para><Para>"The matter is not that simple, as Syria and Hizbullah have no interest in helping us," Tel Aviv University Professor and Syria expert Eyal Zisser said. "I don't see this possibility in the near future."  </Para><Para>Speaking to The Daily Star, a source close to Hizbullah said: "The main issue is about occupied land, and Israel has to leave it, as simple as that.  </Para><Para>"UN resolutions demand they pull out, unconditionally, and so it is Israel's problem not ours if they feel pressured to pull out."  </Para><Para>Israeli concerns stem from the announcement made in mid-March by top Lebanese officials in support of efforts at the UN to confirm that the farms belong to Lebanon.  </Para><Para>Lebanon claims the Shebaa Farms, which have been controlled by Israel since it occupied the Golan Heights from Syria in the 1967 Arab-Israeli war, are Lebanese.  </Para><Para>The U.N. says the farms are Syrian and that Syria and Israel should negotiate their fate.  </Para><Para>However, U.N. envoy to Lebanon Terje Roed-Larsen said in Riyadh last month that the identity of Shebaa was a matter to be resolved between Lebanon and Syria.  </Para><Para>"When the two countries come to an agreement then they can go to the U.N. for a resolution. Until that happens, the Blue Line must be respected," he said.  </Para><Para>However, Syria objects to the scheme and, despite announcing several times that the farms are Lebanese, has refused to send the UN official papers to that end.  </Para><Para>The paper added: "Hizbullah is likely to find a new pretext in the form of seven villages currently in Israeli territory, which the Lebanese group said in the past are part of Lebanon." - With Naharnet  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Daily Star Staff  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>