<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060409e24a00001" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060410"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>POLITICS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Damascus denies providing Shebaa map to UN; World body continues to view area as part of occupied syria  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- BEIRUT: Syria said Sunday that it had not sent the United Nations any map of the Shebaa Farms and the Golan Heights. Damascus was responding to reports and to a recent map issued by the UN Security Council published by a local daily that show the disputed farms as part of Syrian territory.  </Para><Para>This comes as Beirut is trying to establish the Lebanese identity of the farms. The Lebanese government has repeatedly asked Syria to provide the UN with written evidence to document Lebanon's sovereignty over the farms.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>An-Nahar newspaper published the map showing the farms as part of the Golan Heights, in addition to a report issued at the time by UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan regarding the extension of the mandate of the UN Disengagement Observer Force (UNDOF) in the area. At the time, Syria approved the report and did not issue a complaint claiming Shebaa was not part of the Golan Heights.  </Para><Para>An-Nahar stated that "documents relevant to UN Security Council Resolution 1648, issued on Dec. 21, 2005, and pertaining to the extension of the mandate of the UN Disengagement Observer Force (UNDOF), along with the map, prove the Syrian identity of the Shebaa Farms."  </Para><Para>UNDOF was established in May 1974 to supervise the cease-fire called for by the Security Council and the agreement on disengagement between Syrian and Israeli forces of May 31, 1974.  </Para><Para>Annan's report gave an account of UNDOF's activities during the last six months pursuant to the mandate contained in Security Council Resolution 350 of May, 31, 1974 and extended in subsequent resolutions, most recently resolution 1605 of June, 17, 2005. The report states that "during the period under review, the cease-fire in the Israel-Syria sector was maintained and the area of operations of UNDOF remained generally quiet, except in the Shebaa Farms area (Area 6), which experienced activity originating from the area of operation of the United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon (UNIFIL)."  </Para><Para>"The situation in the Israel-Syria sector has remained generally quiet and UNDOF has continued to perform its function effectively with the cooperation of Syrian and Israeli parties," the report added.  </Para><Para>Nevertheless, Annan said "the situation in the Middle East is very tense and is likely to remain so, unless and until a comprehensive settlement covering all aspects of the Middle East problem can be reached."  </Para><Para>He added: "Under the prevailing circumstances, I consider the continued presence of UNDOF in the area to be essential. I therefore recommend that the Security Council extend the mandate of the Force for a further period of six months, until June 30, 2006.  </Para><Para>"The government of the Syrian Arab Republic has given its assent to the proposed extension. The government of Israel has also expressed its agreement," he added.  </Para><Para>In an interview with Lebanese Broadcasting Corporation (LBC), Lebanese Forces MP George Adwan urged Damascus to define the identity of Shebaa Farms. He added, however, that he was "not surprised that the UN considered them Syrian."  </Para><Para>"The UN has stated its position through various meetings between Annan and Premier Fouad Siniora and MP Walid Jumblatt, as well as through Terje Roed-Larsen's statements in Lebanon," he said.  </Para><Para>He added that Syria was still not considering Lebanon a "sovereign, free and independent country."  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Majdoline Hatoum  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>