<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="FLSS000020060411e24b0001b" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060411"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>FOREIGN</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>PLOT TO KILL HEZBOLLAH CHIEF FOILED, ARMY SAYS NINE SUSPECTS ROUNDED UP IN CONSPIRACY AGAINST CLERIC.  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>BEIRUT, Lebanon  </Para><Para>Military intelligence has arrested terrorists who planned to assassinate the leader of Hezbollah, Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, a senior Lebanese military official said Monday.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>The plot was "in the phase of intentions" and had not reached "the phase of implementation," the Lebanese official said.  </Para><Para>He said that nine Lebanese and Palestinian suspects were detained and would be handed to a military prosecutor today for more questioning and indictment.  </Para><Para>The newspaper As-Safir reported Monday that military intelligence had arrested the plotters last week after they were seen acting suspiciously near Hezbollah's headquarters in the southern Beirut district of Haret Horeik.  </Para><Para>Authorities were looking for more members of the plot, the paper said.  </Para><Para>The military official said some of As-Safir's details were true, "but others are not so accurate."  </Para><Para>Nasrallah's political adviser, Hussein Khalil, confirmed the report of the assassination plot and arrests.  </Para><Para>The foiled attack on one of Lebanon's top Shiite clerics and politicians came as fears of sectarian strife have rippled through the Middle East.  </Para><Para>Last week, Arab diplomats said intelligence officers from Iraq's mostly Sunni neighbors have been meeting secretly to coordinate their governments' strategies in case a religious war erupts in Iraq.  </Para><Para>Hezbollah, which draws its support from the Shiites, Lebanon's largest single sect, has rejected giving up its weapons in line with a 2004 U.N. Security Council resolutions, maintaining it still needs them to fight Israel's occupation of a disputed part of south Lebanon.  </Para><Para>In an interview with Hezbollah's Al-Manar TV station, Khalil refused to make a direct accusation but he blamed "the enemies of Lebanon and the enemies of the [Arab] nation," in an apparent reference to Israel.  </Para><Para>The As-Safir newspaper said the terrorists plotting against Hezbollah's chief had planned to fire armor-piercing rockets at Nasrallah's car when he traveled to central Beirut for the next session of the national dialogue among Lebanon's faction leaders.  </Para><Para>The paper also reported that military intelligence had seized such rockets in a raid on the plotters' hideout.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>By Joseph Panossian  The Associated Press  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright 2006, South Florida Sun-Sentinel. All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>