<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="JPST000020060406e24600032" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060406"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>Features</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>From our Archives  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>65 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 6, 1941, The Palestine Post announced that US President Franklin Delano Roosevelt approved the allocation of another $500 million from the $7 billion Lease and Lend funds for the construction of 212 merchant ships in 50 shipyards, intended for Allied use.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>British forces in North Africa announced a threatening new development: the presence of German troops, first reported the previous month, which currently supported the Italian army in a powerful counterattack on Benghazi. This time the German units initiated the attack. The outflanked and outnumbered British troops were withdrawing in good order. The fall of Benghazi was expected.  </Para><Para>The RAF heavily bombed the two German battleships, Scharnhorst and Gneisenau, caught at Brest.  </Para><Para>50 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 6, 1956, The Jerusalem Post reported that six Israelis were wounded in an artillery duel, provoked by Egyptian mortars stationed within the Gaza Strip. Egypt claimed some 140 casualties. Five Negev border settlements suffered from prolonged Egyptian mortar and artillery fire.  </Para><Para>On the eve of his departure for Egypt, the first station of his mission to the Middle East recommended by the UN Security Council, UN Secretary-General Dag Hammarskjold told the press that he expected that "something will be done." He did not seem to be overly optimistic.  </Para><Para>British Prime Minister Sir Anthony Eden sent a "crisis message" to US President Dwight Eisenhower, asking for assistance in defending the British Red Sea positions against Saudi Arabian and Yemenite attacks and for more concrete support in dealing with Jordan, Iraq and Egypt.  </Para><Para>The US International Cooperation Administration procured oil and petroleum worth $4.25m. for Israel.  </Para><Para>25 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 6, 1981, The Jerusalem Post reported that visiting US Secretary of State Alexander Haig urged Israel to think big in terms of regional security and the Soviet threat, while Israel attempted to impress upon him our prime concerns, like the arms race with Saudi Arabia, the Syrian interference in Lebanon, the stalling by Egypt of the autonomy negotiations, the need to conclude policing arrangements for Sinai and the prospects of still closer cooperation with the US.  </Para><Para>The noted British writer Graham Greene visited Israel.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Alexander Zvielli  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright (c) 2006 Bell &amp; Howell Information and Learning Company. All rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>