<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="JPST000020060411e24a0002u" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060410"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>Features</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>From Our Archives  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>65 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 10, 1941, The Palestine Post reported that an estimated 40,000 to 60,000 British, Australian, Palestinian and other Allied troops, which had so far landed in Greece, hoped to stop the speedy German advance by setting up a defense line near Mount Olympus. Meanwhile Athens announced the fall of Salonica, but insisted that the Greek troops enjoyed an "exceptional success" against stopping the new Italian offensive in Albania. Yugoslav troops, valiantly attempting to stop the German advance, also entered Albania. Belgrade was heavily bombed by the Luftwaffe. The RAF continued to bomb the huge German troop concentrations moving into Yugoslavia and Greece.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>British Prime Minister Winston Churchill warned Vichy France against its continued assistance to the German war effort. He forecast a German attempt to secure Ukraine and oil fields in the Caucasian mountains.  </Para><Para>Canada and Australia enlisted more troops for British defense needs.  </Para><Para>General de Gaulle visited the Free French troops stationed in Palestine.  </Para><Para>50 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 10, 1956, The Jerusalem Post reported that Israeli forces in the Negev killed nine marauders and caught another four of the Egyptian fedayeen gang after they murdered Arye Glueck, 42, of Beersheba, in the Nitzana demilitarized zone. A total of 32 attacks on civilians and transport were recorded in the Negev during the previous 48 hours. Many water pipelines were severely damaged.  </Para><Para>UN Secretary-General Dag Hammarskjold, who had just arrived from Beirut for short consultations in Israel, flew again to Cairo, apparently to urge the Egyptians to accept a cease-fire. The US sent urgent, undisclosed messages to both Jerusalem and Cairo.  </Para><Para>25 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 10, 1981, The Jerusalem Post reported that IDF planes bombed terrorist bases in Lebanon. The government decided to double its efforts in the Golan settlement drive.  </Para><Para>The bombardment of Christian targets in Beirut and Zahle by Syria and the PLO put the West Bank Christians in an uncomfortable position. Palestinian Christian leaders admitted to embarrassment, anger and frustration at the awkward situation of the Lebanese Christians.  </Para><Para>West Bank youth disrupted traffic in the administered areas on what they called "Deir Yassin Day."  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Alexander Zvielli  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright (c) 2006 Bell &amp; Howell Information and Learning Company. All rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>