<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="LBA0000020060403e243001r9" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060403"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Lebanon leaders set deadline to agree on president  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>BEIRUT, April 3 (Reuters) - Lebanon's political leaders, meeting to end a political crisis that has paralysed the country, set their next session on April 28 as the deadline to try to agree on the fate of pro-Syrian President Emile Lahoud.  </Para><Para>"We have agreed to delay the dialogue session until Friday April 28 to decide the issue of the presidency, positively or negatively," Parliament Speaker Nabih Berri said after the latest round of talks on Monday.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Rival political leaders have been meeting at high-level talks for the past month to try to find a way out of political disagreements that have brought decision-making to a halt.  </Para><Para>Berri said the politicians would try to agree whether or not to replace Lahoud, who has been under pressure from anti-Syrian politicians to resign, but if there is no agreement the file would be closed and the talks would move on to the last issue on the agenda, the arms of anti-Israeli Hizbollah.  </Para><Para>A political source said rival politicians were unlikely to agree one way or the other at the talks, though anti-Syrian figures have in the past threatened to use other means, such as demonstrations, to maintain pressure on Lahoud to resign.  </Para><Para>They see Lahoud as the last vestige of Syrian tutelage over Lebanon after Damascus withdrew troops from its neighbour last year amid international pressure and Lebanese protest over the assassination of former Lebanese Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri.  </Para><Para>Many Lebanese blamed Syria, which controlled Lebanese politics and security at the time, for the murder but it denies any role. Ties with Syria have been strained ever since.  </Para><Para>Lebanon's parliament extended Lahoud's term by three years in 2004 under what anti-Syrian politicians, who now form the largest bloc in the 128-seat assembly, say was Syrian pressure.  </Para><Para>It would require a two-thirds majority in parliament to scrap that extension, so political consensus at the highest level would be key to any change. But even the anti-Syrian bloc has been unable to decide on a consensus replacement.  </Para><Para>Monday's talks came days after anti-Syrian ministers stormed out of a cabinet meeting following a spat with Lahoud, who has vowed to serve until the end of his term in 2007.  </Para><Para>Lahoud and anti-Syrian Prime Minister Fouad Siniora clashed at the Arab summit last month over a summit statement supporting Lebanon's resistance -- a reference to Hizbollah, the only Lebanese group to retain weapons after the 1975-1990 civil war.  </Para><Para>Hizbollah, which is backed by Syria and Iran, has defended keeping the weapons it used to help end Israel's 22-year occupation of southern Lebanon in 2000, but says it is keen to reach a negotiated deal on the best way to defend the country.  </Para><Para>Some Lebanese say Hizbollah should keep its weapons as a deterrent to Israel, but others say it is time the Shi'ite Muslim group laid down its arms and stuck to politics.  </Para><Para>The leaders have already agreed to disarm Palestinian fighters outside the country's 12 refugee camps within six months and to seek normal diplomatic ties with Damascus.  </Para><Para>The Palestinian factions will be disarmed in line with a U.N. Security Council resolution demanding foreign armies withdraw from Lebanon and militias there disarm.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>By Lin Noueihed  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>LEBANON-DIALOGUE (PICTURE)|LANGEN|AFA|CSA|LBY|RWSA|RWS|REULB|GNS|G|RBN|MD|ABN|M|E|D|RNP|DNP|PGE|SXNA  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 Reuters Limited  </Copyright><Dateline index='field' fid='dln'>April 3, 2006  </Dateline></Article></DistDoc>