<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="NDAY000020060409e24900039" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060409"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>NEWS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>REPORTING FROM THE WEST BANK Shifting from resisting to governing Hamas struggles as it assumes control of Palestinain government  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>RAMALLAH, West Bank  </Para><Para>Naser Shaer, the deputy prime minister of the new Hamas-led Palestinian government, has impeccable credentials: a doctorate from Manchester University in England, a fellowship at New York University and a long tenure teaching Islamic law to college students in his native city of Nablus.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>And in October, he began a five-month stay in an Israeli prison. Last Monday, three weeks after his release, Shaer, 45, shook hands, smiled widely and exchanged kisses with well-wishers at a reception here to introduce him and the militant Palestinian faction's other new ministers to the public.  </Para><Para>Palestinians came and left the spare reception hall throughout the balmy afternoon - young men in jeans chatted with older men in kaffiyehs on one side; women in hijabs socialized on the other.  </Para><Para>"In the morning, in my office, a lot of people - hundreds of people - came to support this government," Shaer said. "There are a lot of things that are challenging us. But by challenging yourself, you make your future."  </Para><Para>Hamas, the 19-year-old Islamic movement that has waged many attacks against Israel, won parliamentary elections in January and assumed control of the Palestinian government and its many thorny problems a week and a half ago.  </Para><Para>Like Shaer, most of the ministers have impressive academic achievements, along with Israeli prison records due to their affiliation with Hamas. Now they are struggling to navigate the transition from armed resistance into professional government without disowning their history or hostility over Israel's four-decade occupation of the West Bank and East Jerusalem.  </Para><Para>Hamas arrives at a critical moment, with little time to prove itself and monumental hurdles to overcome. With negotiations for peace and a Palestinian state at a standstill, Israel's new leaders are threatening to set permanent borders. The Palestinian government is bloated and nearly broke, violent militants run rampant in the Gaza Strip and the defeated Fatah Party is clinging to patronage and power. Meanwhile, Western governments that brand Hamas a terrorist group are working to isolate it and starve it of funds.  </Para><Para>"It's very difficult to convince them you don't drink blood - I had this problem with my American friends in Iowa," said Finance Minister Omar Abdel Razeq, 47, an economist with a doctorate from Iowa State University who finished a three-month Israeli prison term - his second - last month.  </Para><Para>"We hope people try to ask themselves why. Why would a 19-year-old or a 20-year-old explode themselves?" Razeq said. "There are many reasons ... the main one is the humiliation we are living in occupation. That doesn't mean suicide bombings are useful all the time."  </Para><Para>Monday's Ramallah reception featured only some of the ministers because Hamas members in Gaza, including Prime Minister Ismail Haniyeh, can't travel through Israel. The ministers, an assemblage mainly of older, bureaucratic looking men in gray and black suits, sat quietly along the wall, rising as guests entered.  </Para><Para>Justice Minister Ahmed Kalidi was dean of law at An-Najah University in Nablus and helped write the Palestinian constitution. The lone female minister, Mariam Saleh, 53, is a professor of Islamic law at Al-Quds University in Jerusalem and lived for two decades in Saudi Arabia.  </Para><Para>Israelis reportedly have incarcerated 14 of the Hamas government's 24 ministers over more than a decade. Shaer was detained for "endangering security" in the West Bank, according to Israeli army officials. Razeq was indicted on March 9 and faces trial for "membership, activity and holding a position in an illegal organization." Khaled Abu Arafa, the Jerusalem affairs minister, was detained briefly Friday on the way to his new office.  </Para><Para>At the reception, Shaer speculated that half the 400 guests had been arrested at some point.  </Para><Para>"Once you speak angry words, you might be sent tomorrow to a prison," he said. "Anyway, this is our life. This is our people. We are willing to help them, support them, even if that costs us a high price."  </Para><Para>This discordant mixture of modesty and defiance epitomizes Hamas. The reception was without pomp. Eight rows of wooden chairs were lined up in the room, pitchers of water and glasses sat on tables and waiters carried trays of baklava.  </Para><Para>Fatah, the secular faction of the late Yasser Arafat, controlled the Palestinian government for a decade in which corruption and patronage flourished. Hamas, long known for discipline both in its militancy and the social services it has provided, tries to portray itself as disinterested in power, except to serve the people.  </Para><Para>"It's not 'Your Excellency,'" said Nayef Rajoub, the religious affairs minister, reading the opening lines of a letter as he sipped tea in a hotel lobby in Ramallah. "It's 'Brother.' 'Your excellency,' 'Your holiness' - take it out of the dictionary."  </Para><Para>Rajoub, 47, is the younger brother of a former security chief to Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas, the Fatah leader. An early Hamas member, Rajoub began preaching Islam as a boy and wears a long beard. He's been imprisoned several times since 1989 and was deported to Lebanon in 1992. When Israel comes up, humility turns to stridence.  </Para><Para>"They represent the Nazis and we are the victims, the same as Jews were victims of the Nazis," Rajoub said.  </Para><Para>Such rhetoric and Hamas' refusal to recognize Israel led the European Union and the United States Friday to cut off hundreds of millions of dollars in aid. Israel has withheld more than $50 million in taxes collected for the Palestinians - a third of the monthly budget. When Hamas held its first cabinet meeting Wednesday, Haniyeh said the coffers were empty.  </Para><Para>"Hamas now has been confronted earlier than they expected with this crisis," said Khaled Duzdar, an economist with the Israel/Palestine Center for Research and Information, a Jerusalem think tank.  </Para><Para>The ministers want to take the focus off Hamas. "There is a difference between Hamas and the Palestinian government," said Sameer Abu-Eishe, 45, the planning minister, who is trying to line up foreign aid.  </Para><Para>Mark Regev, an Israeli Foreign Ministry spokesman, said future relations would depend on "to what extent do they encourage terrorism." Militarily, Hamas has declared a cease-fire but reserved the right to resume attacks.  </Para><Para>Diplomatically, the group appears to be grappling with how to proceed. Haniyeh alluded to possible talks between Abbas and Israel, and an ultimate softening of Hamas' position. Then Foreign Minister Mahmoud Zahar told Chinese journalists he dreamed of a map without Israel on his wall.  </Para><Para>On Tuesday, Zahar moderated his position in a letter to the United Nations, saying Hamas wanted to live independently, "side by side with our neighbors," and implying it might accept a "two-state solution." But later, Zahar backtracked again, emphasizing he still did not recognize Israel's right to exist.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>MICHAEL ROTHFELD  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'>1) AP Photo - Deputy Prime Minister Naser Shaer leads a cabinet meeting 2) AFP / Getty Images Photo-On March 28, incoming Palestinian Prime Minister Ismail Haniyeh, center, gestures to Hamas supporters in Gaza City celebrating
 parliament's approval of his cabinet.  </Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright 2006, Newsday. All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>