<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="ORSE000020060408e24800020" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060408"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>A SECTION</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>U.S. will cut millions set aside for Palestinians  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>WASHINGTON -- The Bush administration said Friday that it will cut or suspend a total of about $306 million in U.S. assistance and development money earmarked for Palestinians because the U.S.-designated terrorist group Hamas has assumed control of the Palestinian Authority, which governs the West Bank and Gaza Strip.  </Para><Para>In addition, about $105 million is being cut from other assistance programs but will be redirected to international organizations and nonprofit groups working with Palestinians on education and health projects or to emergency-assistance efforts for refugees scattered in the Palestinian territories, Jordan, Lebanon and Syria.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Despite the effort to redirect those funds, the net loss in taxpayer-financed assistance for the Palestinians looks stiff. State Department officials said the roughly $306 million the administration is cutting or freezing is about half of all unspent American cash earmarked for the territories in the past several years or currently in the pipeline.  </Para><Para>European Union officials also said Friday that they would halt a payment of about $37 million meant to provide direct support to the Palestinian Authority. On Monday, European foreign ministers are scheduled to discuss what they will do about hundreds of millions more in assistance their nations provide to the Palestinians.  </Para><Para>In February, Israel announced it was cutting off about $50 million a month in duties it collects for the authority.  </Para><Para>The Bush administration and most of its international allies have insisted they will not support a Hamas-led government unless it rejects violence, accepts Israel's right to exist and agrees to abide by standing peace accords. The destruction of Israel is a central tenet of Hamas.  </Para><Para>The Bush administration's announcement Friday comes after an in-depth review of all U.S.-financed projects and assistance programs benefiting Palestinians.  </Para><Para>Coordinated with terrorism-finance experts at the Justice Department and the Treasury Department, the examination covered about $600 million in assistance. It was necessitated by the sweeping Hamas victory in January's parliamentary elections and U.S. laws forbidding American tax dollars from going to those designated by the U.S. government as foreign terrorists.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Cam Simpson Chicago Tribune  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>6 killed as Israeli aircraft fires missiles into car carrying
Palestinian militants. Page A9  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright 2006, Orlando Sentinel. All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>