<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="OSTDJ00020060409e24800001" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060408"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>DJ Egypt's Mubarak: Iraq Close To Civil War -Report  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>CAIRO, Apr 08, 2006 (DJCS via Comtex) --  </Para><Para>In a far-reaching interview Saturday with an Arab satellite channel, Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak warned that an Iraqi civil war was imminent and also said he would work to bring Israelis and Palestinians back to the negotiating table.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>The hourlong interview with Al-Arabiya focused on the region's flashpoints - Iraq and the Palestinian territories - and also addressed Lebanese-Syrian tension and Sudan's Darfur conflict.  </Para><Para>Asked by the interviewer if civil war was at Iraq's door, a troubled-looking Mubarak said it had already passed the threshold.  </Para><Para>"It is not at the door. Civil war has almost started among Shiites, Sunnis, Kurds and those who are coming from Asia," he said. "The situation is uneasy and I don't know how Iraq will be brought together. At the moment, Iraq is almost close to destruction."  </Para><Para>A day earlier, Iraq witnessed its deadliest attack of the year, a bomb at the Shiite Buratha mosque in north Baghdad that killed 85 people. Saturday, a car bomb killed six people near a Shiite shrine south of Baghdad, and fears of more attacks are running high.  </Para><Para>Mubarak warned that a withdrawal of U.S. troops now would only worsen the situation in Iraq and lead to an increase in terrorism across the region.  </Para><Para>"It would be a blow. The war would be inflamed among Iraqis. It would become a theater for a dreadful civil war, and then the terrorist operations will be escalated, not only in Iraq," he said.  </Para><Para>He also questioned the loyalty of Iraq's Shiite Muslims to their home country.  </Para><Para>"Defiantly Iran has influence for Shiites. ... Most of the Shiites are loyal to Iran, and not to the countries they are living in," he said, reflecting a concern among Arab nations that Iran has too much influence in Iraq and that its Shiite-majority Islamic theocracy could spill over into their largely Sunni countries.  </Para><Para>On the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, Mubarak said he would push leaders from both sides to return to the negotiating table.  </Para><Para>Israeli Prime Minister-designate Ehud Olmert, whose party won last week's elections, has already agreed to come to Egypt after he forms his coalition government. Mubarak said he would also invite the Palestinian Liberation Organization, the president of the Palestinian Authority and Hamas to talk with him.  </Para><Para>He denied that his intelligence chief, Omar Suleiman, had asked Hamas to recognize Israel.  </Para><Para>"Neither Omar Suleiman nor anybody else can ask Hamas to recognize Israel," he said. "They have to think and assess a stand."  </Para><Para>"Then we have to help out in starting up negotiations, so that progress would be reached in the road map issue," Mubarak said. The long-stalled "road map" peace plan - sponsored by the U.S., E.U., Russia and the U.N. - calls for an end to Palestinian violence and Jewish settlement building and envisions the establishment of a Palestinian state.  </Para><Para>But Israel refuses to negotiate with Hamas unless the group recognizes Israel, renounces violence and accepts existing peace accords. Hamas, which took power earlier this month after winning parliamentary elections, has said repeatedly it would not revise its positions, though some leaders in the group have hinted at a readiness to moderate.  </Para><Para>Mubarak said a return to peace negotiations was "a must."  </Para><Para>"I don't know if Hamas is going to join them, or someone else. I do not intervene in Palestinian affairs. But I say that certainly there must be a return to the negotiations. If they (the Israelis) want to sit with Hamas, or the PLO, they should sit at the negotiating table and start resolving their problems, for the sake of the people who are suffering," Mubarak said.  </Para><Para>Turning to Lebanon, Mubarak said he supported the U.N. probe into the 2005 assassination of former Lebanese Prime Minister Rafik Hariri. Lebanese opposition blame Syria - which was the main power broker in Lebanon at the time - and the U.N. team has implicated top Syrian and Lebanese officials in the bombing.  </Para><Para>"The inspections should go on, but we should be working on maintaining security in Lebanon, so that the people can live," Mubarak said. "Syrian stability is linked directly with Lebanon's stability and Lebanese stability is linked to Syrian stability."  </Para><Para>He rejected any outside attempt to change the Syrian government - as some believe the U.S. wants to do.  </Para><Para>"We are against changing the regimes. Using force to change regimes is a dangerous issue, because if it is done in one place, it could then happen somewhere else," he said.  </Para><Para>Regarding Sudan, Mubarak reiterated Egypt's opposition to U.N. forces in the troubled western Darfur region and said he had no evidence of massacres or genocide there.  </Para><Para>On the home front, Mubarak dismissed the idea of handing over the presidency to his son, Gamal. Opposition groups and many Egyptians believe Gamal Mubarak, recently named assistant secretary-general of the ruling National Democratic Party, is being groomed to take power.  </Para><Para>(END) Dow Jones Newswires  </Para><Para>04-08-06 1954ET  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright 2006, Comtex News Network.  All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>