<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="T000000020060407e2470005p" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060407"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>Overseas news</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Arab nations quietly bridge the trade gulf with Israelis;Foreign Editor's briefing  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>ISRAEL'S relations with the Palestinians may be frozen. But in one of the subtler shifts in the region, its links with the Gulf Arab countries are warming up.  </Para><Para>The gates won't be thrown open between the two until there is some formal progress in Israeli-Palestinian relations, and that is now out of sight.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>But in a region where most changes are potentially alarming, this one offers hope of greater openness, prosperity and forging of common links.  </Para><Para>One Israeli official said: "We want normal relations with the Arab world, and the Gulf is a natural place to start. We have no quarrel with them."  </Para><Para>Qatar, the maverick of the Arab world, is the only Gulf state formally to recognise Israel. Oman broke off diplomatic relations on the Palestinian uprising of September 2000.  </Para><Para>Commercial links have been strangled by the Arab boycott, set up in 1951 by Arab countries as a way of hurting Israel. But in the past few years, the Gulf states have quietly softened the estrangement.  </Para><Para>The turmoil in Iraq has led some to look for allies. So has Iran, its new hardline government noisily voicing its ambitions of being a regional power.  </Para><Para>So, too, has the uncertainty about the long-term future of Saudi Arabia, the giant of the Arab world. "These ties, with the US, with Israel, all help (the Gulf states) be more independent of us," said one Saudi official. They are not unfriendly to their "older brother", he said, "but it suits them".  </Para><Para>The shift has shown up in diplomatic contacts. Most visibly, the Qatari and Israeli foreign ministers met at the United Nations General Assembly in New York in September.  </Para><Para>Sheikh Hamad bin Jassim bin Jabor al-Thani, who praised Israel for the Gaza withdrawal, said that "Arab countries must take a step towards Israel...in an attempt to come up with a clear vision to the period after Gaza". Qatar is also giving Pounds 3.5 million to build a stadium in Israel for a popular Arab soccer team.  </Para><Para>Since 2000, when Bahrain's crown prince met Shimon Peres, the former Israeli Prime Minister, there have been intermittent, low-key contacts between those countries.  </Para><Para>But the biggest sign of a change has been the withering of the Arab boycott, partly because of the huge lure of trade with the US, Europe and Israel itself.  </Para><Para>In its heyday, after the 1973 Yom Kippur war, the boycott not only banned Israeli companies from trading with Arab countries, but blacklisted companies which did business with blacklisted companies. Chief executives would lose sleep over whether the list, issued by the Office of the Arab Boycott in Damascus, would target them.  </Para><Para>But its grip was weakened by Egypt's peace with Israel in 1978, and by the 1993 Oslo Accords, when many Arab countries partly rescinded it. Syria, Iran and Lebanon remain fervent practioners, among the 22 members of the Arab League, but the office has not convened in strength since 1996.  </Para><Para>In January, the US finally signed a Free Trade Agreement with Bahrain; one of the conditions was that Bahrain drop its opposition to trade with Israel (it says it recognises the need to dismantle the boycott, and is working on it).  </Para><Para>The US already has in place similar agreements with Jordan and Morocco (and Israel itself). The Bush Administration has agreed one with Oman, which Congress is debating now.  </Para><Para>Last year, Saudi Arabia joined the World Trade Organisation. That brought strong pressure, if not a binding condition, to accept trade with Israel.  </Para><Para>At the moment, Israeli commercial figures show only trade with Jordan, Egypt and, of course, Turkey. But there are many anecdotes of how trade between Israel and the Gulf states already takes place, even if the goods do not end up with a "Made in Israel" label. It takes place through third countries, or directly, but labels are stripped off.  </Para><Para>The Arab countries are aware that Israel represents a huge source of technology and know-how, sitting right there on their borders. It was a point that Silvan Shalom, Israeli Foreign Minister, made to them at a UN gathering in Tunis in November.  </Para><Para>But even though politicians and business people are quietly exploring these links, popular opinion in the Arab countries remains an obstacle. While relations between Israel and the Palestinians remain so hostile, popular feelings run very high against more open links.  </Para><Para>Arab shoppers are still loyal to a boycott which their leaders - and companies - are finding a growing frustration.  </Para><Para>(c) Times Newspapers Ltd, 2006   </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Bronwen Maddox  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 Times Newspapers Limited. All rights reserved  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>