<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="TRIB000020060408e24800056" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060408"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>News</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>U.S. to cut aid over Hamas; Government also loses EU cash; Washington to redirect some funds  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>WASHINGTON  </Para><Para>The Bush administration said Friday that it will cut or suspend a total of about $306 million in U.S. assistance and development funds earmarked for Palestinians because the U.S.-designated terrorist group Hamas has assumed control of the Palestinian Authority, which governs the West Bank and Gaza Strip.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>In addition, about $105 million is being cut from other assistance programs but will be redirected to international organizations and non-profit groups working with Palestinians on education and health projects or to emergency assistance efforts for refugees scattered in the Palestinian territories, Jordan, Lebanon and Syria.  </Para><Para>Despite the effort to redirect those funds, the net loss in taxpayer-financed assistance for the Palestinians looks stiff. State Department officials said the roughly $306 million the administration is cutting or freezing comprises about half of all unspent American cash earmarked for the territories in the past several years or currently in the pipeline.  </Para><Para>European Union officials also said Friday that they would halt a payment of about $37 million meant to provide direct support to the Palestinian Authority. On Monday, European foreign ministers are scheduled to discuss what they will do about hundreds of millions more in assistance their nations provide to the Palestinians from their own treasuries.  </Para><Para>Pressure on Hamas  </Para><Para>Friday's announcements increases worldwide pressure on the Hamas-run Palestinian Authority, which is already facing a financial crisis. In February, Israel announced it was cutting off about $50 million a month in duties it collects for the authority, funding that was a lifeline for the government.  </Para><Para>Payroll checks owed to 140,000 Palestinian government-funded employees in the West Bank and Gaza, a major source of cash in the territories, are already a week overdue; they were two weeks late last month and were delivered only because of an emergency payment from the Europeans.  </Para><Para>A reprisal appeared out of the question for April because Hamas assumed control of the government last week.  </Para><Para>"It's going to be very interesting to see whether Hamas can come up with the money to pay salaries this month," said Edward Abington, a former American diplomat who is a consultant to Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas. Elected separately from the Hamas-led parliament, Abbas is not affiliated with the militant group. Administration officials said Friday that there are no immediate plans to fund Abbas' office, a move they had previously considered to maintain some influence in the territories.  </Para><Para>Abington said that it was possible Hamas could find enough money to cover its payrolls for the next couple of months but that a crisis appears inevitable.  </Para><Para>The Bush administration and most of its international allies have insisted they will not support a Hamas-led government unless it rejects violence, accepts Israel's right to exist and agrees to abide by standing peace accords. The destruction of Israel is a central tenet of Hamas philosophy.  </Para><Para>The Bush administration's announcement Friday comes after an in-depth review of all U.S.-financed projects and assistance programs benefiting Palestinians.  </Para><Para>Coordinated with terrorism-finance experts at the Justice Department and the Treasury Department, the examination covered about $600 million in assistance. It was necessitated by the Hamas victory in January's parliamentary elections and U.S. laws forbidding American tax dollars from going to those designated by the U.S. government as foreign terrorists.  </Para><Para>The Bush administration supported the Palestinian elections but was caught off-guard by the Hamas victory.  </Para><Para>Although there was little question the administration had to cut $45 million in direct funding for the Palestinian Authority because it is now controlled by Hamas, it was unclear Friday how much discretion the White House and State Department exercised in making the other cuts. It was also unclear why more of the funds could not be redirected to humanitarian programs that did not involve channeling funds through the Palestinian Authority.  </Para><Para>Administration officials said they are intent on not providing any assistance that might even indirectly benefit the Hamas government.  </Para><Para>The single largest hit appears to be a $130 million cut in infrastructure projects, including such things as roads, sewers and the delivery of potable water. Other cuts include $20 million for economic programs, such as private enterprise development, and a $4 million cut for community policing.  </Para><Para>`Subject to further review'  </Para><Para>An estimated $165 million of the cash being cut or frozen remains "subject to further review," the State Department said. Those funds were for unspecified "ongoing and planned projects."  </Para><Para>Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice, in a statement, made no mention of the total amount of funds being cut or frozen. Instead, she emphasized an increase in what she called "basic humanitarian assistance," saying that such aid for the Palestinians "will increase by 57 percent."  </Para><Para>However, the category Rice described as increasing includes funding the administration has not previously categorized as humanitarian assistance, including funding for education and the UN Relief and Works Agency for Palestinian Refugees.  </Para><Para>----------  </Para><Para>csimpson@tribune.com  </Para><Para>PHOTO: Food is distributed to Palestinians this week in Gaza City. On Friday, the U.S. said it will redirect assistance to international groups working with Palestinians. Dallas Morning News photo by Barbara Davidson.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>By Cam Simpson, Washington Bureau  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'>PHOTO  </Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright 2006, Chicago Tribune. All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>