<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="AFPR000020060410e24a00469" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060410"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Middle East news summary  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>NICOSIA, April 10, 2006 (AFP) -  </Para><Para>Top Middle East stories on Monday:  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Iraq  </Para><Para>BAGHDAD: Sunni Arab, Kurdish and secularist leaders emphatically rejected Iraqi Prime Minister Ibrahim Jaafari staying on in his post, possibly sealing the embattled Shiite premier's political fate.  </Para><Para>Iraq-media-kidnap  </Para><Para>BAGHDAD: An Iraqi employee of Agence France-Presse, accountant Salah Jali al-Gharrawi, was kidnapped on April 4 in central Baghdad and the agency has no news of his fate.  </Para><Para>Germany-Iraq-kidnap  </Para><Para>BERLIN: German Foreign Minister Frank-Walter Steinmeier hailed a video of two German hostages held in Iraq as confirmation that they are still alive and said the government was confident it would secure their release.  </Para><Para>Mideast  </Para><Para>RAMALLAH, West Bank: Palestinian leader Mahmud Abbas urged Israel to abandon its efforts to isolate his Hamas-led government as financial pressure on the Islamist regime intensified.  </Para><Para>EU-Mideast-Palestinian-aid  </Para><Para>LUXEMBOURG: The European Union vowed to stand by the beleaguered Palestinian people despite suspending aid to their Hamas-run governnment, denying the funding cutoff amounts to "blackmail."  </Para><Para>Mideast-Palestinian-aid-Algeria  </Para><Para>GAZA CITY: The Hamas-led Palestinian government still faces a 120 million dollar monthly budget shortfall, despite having received 35 million dollars from Algeria, finance minister Omar Abdulrazeq said.  </Para><Para>Iran-nuclear-politics-Ahmadinejad-UN  </Para><Para>TEHRAN: President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad vowed he would not back down "one iota" over Iran's nuclear programme, again rejecting a UN Security Council demand for Tehran to freeze sensitive enrichment work.  </Para><Para>Lebanon-justice-Hezbollah-arrest  </Para><Para>BEIRUT: Lebanon denied a report that nine had been arrested in a plot to kill Hezbollah chief Sheikh Hassan Nasrallah, but confirmed the men had been detained for planning an attack "against the state".  </Para><Para>afp  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>AFP  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright Agence France-Presse, 2006 All reproduction and presentation rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>