<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="AFPR000020060405e245003ne" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060405"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Middle East news summary  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>NICOSIA, April 5, 2006 (AFP) -  </Para><Para>Top Middle East stories on Wednesday:  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Iraq-politics  </Para><Para>BAGHDAD: Embattled Iraqi Prime Minister Ibrahim al-Jaafari remained defiant after calls from a vice president for him to step down to break weeks of deadlock on the formation of a new government.  </Para><Para>Iraq-Saddam-trial  </Para><Para>BAGHDAD: Former Iraqi dictator Saddam Hussein dismissed evidence linking him to the mass killing of Shiite villagers as he launched a new tirade of abuse against his tumultuous trial.  </Para><Para>Mideast-Palestinian-UN-peace-Israel  </Para><Para>JERUSALEM: Israel reacted sceptically to an unprecedented Middle East peace overture from Hamas foreign minister Mahmud al-Zahar to UN chief Kofi Annan, seeing no change in Hamas's refusal to recognise the Jewish state and accusing it of playing games.  </Para><Para>Mideast-Israel-politics  </Para><Para>JERUSALEM: Israel's Acting Prime Minister Ehud Olmert looked set to invite into his ruling coalition the ultra-nationalist Yisrael Beitenu party, which advocates the forced deportation of Arab Israelis.  </Para><Para>Mideast-Palestinian-politics-economy  </Para><Para>GAZA CITY: Prime minister Ismail Haniya said that the Palestinian coffers were completely empty as he hosted the first regular cabinet meeting of his Hamas-led government.  </Para><Para>Iraq-US-unrest-pilots-video  </Para><Para>PARIS: An Al-Qaeda-led coalition of rebel groups in Iraq posted a video on the Internet purporting to show the mutilated body of one of two pilots of a US helicopter it claimed to have downed southwest of Baghdad.  </Para><Para>Iran-military-US  </Para><Para>TEHRAN: The head of Iran's elite Revolutionary Guards said the United States must accept the Islamic Republic as a regional power which cannot be left isolated.  </Para><Para>Kuwait-oil-refinery  </Para><Para>KUWAIT CITY: Kuwait has prequalified 11 international companies for the construction of a new 6.3-billion-dollar oil refinery with a capacity of more than 600,000 barrels per day.  </Para><Para>Yemen-weather-floods-toll  </Para><Para>SANAA: At least 25 people have been killed in Yemen in floods and lightning brought on by three days of torrential rains, the defense ministry's website said.  </Para><Para>Lebanon-politics-economy  </Para><Para>BEIRUT: The Beirut government was due to discuss a long-awaited reform programme ahead of an international donor conference to help Lebanon out of its economic and political crises.  </Para><Para>afp.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>AFP  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright Agence France-Presse, 2006 All reproduction and presentation rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>