<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="AFPR000020060409e2490076i" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060409"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Middle East news summary  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>NICOSIA, April 9, 2006 (AFP) -  </Para><Para>Top Middle East stories on Sunday:  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Iraq-Iran-Egypt-Shiites-Mubarak  </Para><Para>CAIRO: Iraq and its powerful neighbour Iran were fuming over comments by Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, a major broker in Middle East politics, about Iraqi civil war and Shiites' allegiance to Tehran.  </Para><Para>Iraq  </Para><Para>BAGHDAD: Iraq's Shiite parliament bloc formed a committee to decide the fate of embattled Prime Minister Ibrahim Jaafari as deadly violence erupted on the third anniversary of Saddam Hussein's fall.  </Para><Para>Mideast-unrest  </Para><Para>GAZA CITY: The armed wing of the governing Palestinian movement Hamas, under huge international pressure to renounce violence, vowed to avenge a weekend of Israeli strikes which has left 15 people dead.  </Para><Para>Mideast-Israel-politics  </Para><Para>JERUSALEM: Ehud Olmert's Kadima party, winners of last month's Israeli election, hosted talks with other factions to decide the make-up of a coalition which is set to fix the Jewish state's final borders.  </Para><Para>Israel-Sharon-Olmert-politics  </Para><Para>JERUSALEM: Israel's government will on Tuesday declare coma-stricken Prime Minister Ariel Sharon as "permanently incapacitated" and name Ehud Olmert as his successor, a justice ministry official said.  </Para><Para>Mideast-Israel-Palestinian-Hamas-diplomacy  </Para><Para>JERUSALEM: Israel's Acting Prime Minister Ehud Olmert announced that his government would boycott foreign diplomats who meet with members of the new Hamas-led Palestinian government.  </Para><Para>Iraq-unrest-US-Hamaniyah  </Para><Para>BAGHDAD: US forces, using air support, killed eight suspected insurgents in an early morning assault in the vicinity of Hamaniyah, west of Baghdad, the military said.  </Para><Para>Iraq-politics-unrest-Britain  </Para><Para>LONDON: British Foreign Secretary Jack Straw reaffirmed his view that Iraq was not in a state of civil war, despite comments to the contrary by a number of senior Iraqi and Arab politicians.  </Para><Para>Germany-Iraq-kidnap  </Para><Para>BERLIN: The German foreign ministry said it had received a new video believed to be of two German hostages who have been held in Iraq since late January.  </Para><Para>Iran-nuclear-politics-Iraq-drone  </Para><Para>TEHRAN: Iran has shot down an unmanned surveillance plane in the south amid reports that the United States is planning military strikes on Iranian nuclear facilities, a press report said.  </Para><Para>Iran-nuclear-politics-US  </Para><Para>TEHRAN: Iran branded as "psychological warfare" media reports that the US military was planning air strikes to force Tehran to abandon its controversial nuclear program.  </Para><Para>Jordan-oil-economy  </Para><Para>AMMAN: Jordan's opposition Islamic Action Front party (IAF) accused the authorities of detaining dozens of its members for distributing leaflets against fuel hikes.  </Para><Para>Lebanon-Syria-Hariri-UN-probe  </Para><Para>KUWAIT CITY: The former head of Syrian military intelligence in Lebanon, Rustom Ghazaleh, denied any role in the murder of former Lebanese prime minister Rafiq Hariri.  </Para><Para>afp  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>AFP  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright Agence France-Presse, 2006 All reproduction and presentation rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>