<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="AFPR000020060411e24b003pj" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060411"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Sharon: Israel's warrior leaves the battleground  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>JERUSALEM, April 11, 2006 (AFP) -  </Para><Para>Ariel Sharon, whose reign as Israeli prime minister was declared over Tuesday, was a hawkish general turned statesman who pioneered plans to redraw the nation's borders and revolutionised the political landscape.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>For decades, the 78-year-old "Bulldozer" made it his mission to safeguard national security. By the end of his tenure, he was convinced Israel needed to separate from the Palestinians and unilaterally determine its own borders.  </Para><Para>After removing Israeli troops and settlers from the Gaza Strip in September following a 38-year occupation, Sharon abandoned his right-wing Likud party to form a new centrist grouping to fulfil what he saw as an historic calling.  </Para><Para>In an extraordinary if controversial career stretching back more than half a century, his departure from the political scene leaves a void likely to be felt far beyond the narrow confines of Israel.  </Para><Para>Hailed by US President George W. Bush as "a man who had a vision for peace", he was praised also by his often frosty ally Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak as a "courageous" leader who could have brought peace to the Middle East.  </Para><Para>Born in British-mandate Palestine on February 27, 1928 to parents from Belarus, the general, whom may regarded as a war hero, summed himself up as Warrior in the title of his autobiography.  </Para><Para>Impetuous and daring, with a cutting sense of humour, he proved himself an artful soldier and shrewd politician who pioneered some of the most far-reaching changes in Israeli history.  </Para><Para>He was first elected prime minister in February 2001, just months after walking across the disputed Al-Aqsa/Temple Mount compound in Jerusalem and sparking the second Palestinian uprising.  </Para><Para>His critics charged the visit was a cynical political ploy, that Sharon knew the walkabout would spark violence and was counting on the Israeli electorate to believe he was the only man strong enough for the premiership.  </Para><Para>But while his administration was initially seen as the most hawkish in history, less than four years later it set a precedent for the future by recalling Jews from Palestinian territory occupied in the 1967 Middle East war.  </Para><Para>The pullout, the crowning achievement of his career, earnt him plaudits from around the world but made implacable enemies of his former friends and allies on the nationalist right, significantly weakening their lobby status.  </Para><Para>Still nothing could redeem him in the eyes of his Palestinian foes. Shortly after his massive stroke on January 4, militant group Hamas said the Middle East would be better off without him.  </Para><Para>Likewise, his critics on the Israeli right regarded him as a sell-out whose strategy had helped hand power to Hamas in a January Palestinian election.  </Para><Para>Sharon began his military career when he was 17 and first came to prominence on the battlefield in Israel's wars against Arab states such as Egypt.  </Para><Para>Twice wounded, he quickly acquired a reputation for chilling reprisals and a maverick tendency to do whatever he wanted.  </Para><Para>He saw action as a general in the 1967 Six Day War and was recalled from retirement in the 1973 Yom Kippur when he famously led his troops across Egypt's Suez canal.  </Para><Para>Dubbed "the Bulldozer" both for his style and physique, to this day, Sharon is also remembered as the "Butcher of Beirut" for the massacres of Palestinian refugees at Sabra and Shatila in Lebanon while Israeli troops looked on.  </Para><Para>As defence minister, Sharon mastermined the disastrous 1982 invasion of Israel's northern neighbourhood and siege of Yasser Arafat's Palestine Liberation Organisation headquarters in Beirut.  </Para><Para>The operation ultimately cost him his job -- forced to resign as defence chief if not from the cabinet after being held "indirectly responsible" for the Sabra and Shatila killings.  </Para><Para>Yet he slowly rebuilt his reputation first as infrastructure and then foreign minister before becoming leader in 2000 of the Likud, the party he helped develop, and rising to the pinnacle of government.  </Para><Para>Last November, he left to set up a new party, Kadima, frustrated with hardliners opposed to the Gaza pullout and any further concessions in the occupied West Bank, effectively redrawing the political landscape in Israel.  </Para><Para>His final political gamble was vindicated in the March 28 election when Kadima made Israeli history as the first new party to win its first election.  </Para><Para>Left rudderless without Sharon, the rump Likud suffered a humiliating defeat, leaving around two thirds of MPs in the new parliament in favour of plans to redraw the borders of Israel, drawn up by Sharon's heir Ehud Olmert.  </Para><Para>Away from the political limelight, he was a passionate farmer on his family ranch but his personal life was blighted by tragedy.  </Para><Para>His first wife Margalith was killed in a car crash in 1962. His second wife, her younger sister Lily, died of cancer five years ago.  </Para><Para>His sons Omri and Gilad have worked closely with Sharon, but the former has been sentenced to prison for corruption over political funraising for his father. A third son, Gur, died in 1967 after being shot playing with his father's rifle.  </Para><Para>bur-jm/co/txw  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>BUR  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright Agence France-Presse, 2006 All reproduction and presentation rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>