<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060406e2470000e" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060407"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>POLITICS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Southerners who fled after Israel's withdrawal set to return with promise of fair hearing  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- BEIRUT: Some 60 Lebanese who fled to Israel during the Israeli withdrawal from South Lebanon in May 2000 will be returning to Lebanon in accordance with a February understanding between Hizbullah and the Free Patriotic Movement. "The understanding between Hizbullah and the FPM has removed the psychological obstacles that have stalled the return of Lebanese from occupied Palestine," said FPM member Gibran Bassil on Thursday.  </Para><Para>Two months ago, Hizbullah leader Sayyed Hassan Nasrallah and Michel Aoun announced a 10-point joint statement of cooperation pledging that Lebanese who had fled to Israel in the aftermath of the May 2000 liberation of South Lebanon would be treated "fairly" by the Lebanese judicial system if they chose to come home.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Bassil said that Hizbullah and the FPM have completed all the necessary paperwork and legal procedures required for the return of Lebanese citizens "who have not received any sentences in absentia," mainly the elderly, women and children.  </Para><Para>"These people fled to Israel out of fear and should not fear coming back as conditions have changed in Lebanon. Now we have an independent judiciary that functions justly and freely and will assist in the return of those concerned and respect their rights," said Bassil.  </Para><Para>The first batch of 10 people is expected to arrive in Lebanon before Easter, with a larger group expected to return in mid-May.  </Para><Para>Most of those set to return are relatives of several hundred former soldiers and officers in the Israeli-allied South Lebanon Army. The SLA fighters fled with their families to Israel in 2000 for fear of reprisal attacks had they remained in Lebanon after Israeli troops ended their 22-year occupation.  </Para><Para>As for those who were sentenced in absentia by military tribunals for entering "enemy territory" and collaborating with an occupying power, Bassil said it will take time to resolve their case but that it will be settled "eventually."  </Para><Para>There are some 2,600 Lebanese in Israel, of which 200 who have not been convicted of a crime against their country are scheduled to return to Lebanon before the end of June, according to As-Safir.  </Para><Para>The Lebanese daily reported that the cases of nearly 100 former SLA militiamen will not be part of the understanding. - Rym Ghazal  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Rym Ghazal  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>