<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060403e2440000i" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060404"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>POLITICS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>News in Brief Published on 04/04/2006  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- Israel reduces border activity after state of alert  </Para><Para>A few hours after announcing a state of alert on the Lebanese border, The National News Agency (NNA) reported on Monday that the Israeli forces reduced military action along its border with Lebanon and moved its vehicles to roads further in.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>But military vehicles equipped with field and machine guns remained, seen standing on the full alert particularly in the military outposts that are close or located along the internationally drawn Blue Line.  </Para><Para>The initiative was taken soon after the Israeli state announced the Lebanese resistance is planning to kidnap two Israeli officers and transport them to the Lebanese territories.  </Para><Para>The NNA said the UNIFIL forces in Lebanon also increased their military field activities and intensified monitoring on both sides of the border.  </Para><Para>SOLIDA censures military for attack on students  </Para><Para>The SOLIDA movement (Support for Lebanese Detained Arbitrarily) denounced on Monday the violence reportedly perpetrated by military personnel on March 30 as well as the resulting arbitrary arrests, and demanded that the Lebanese government open an investigation to identify those responsible.  </Para><Para>On March 30, violent clashes erupted between students affiliated with the Lebanese Forces Party, who were celebrating their victory in the student government elections of Lebanese University, Information and Documentation Section, and Lebanese Army troops. Sources said that the students were suddenly attacked and beaten up by soldiers who then arrested eight of them and loaded them into trucks where they were beaten again. After their release later in the evening, the students were notified that they were prohibited from expressing their political opinion.  </Para><Para>Survey of poultry farms ordered in South  </Para><Para>South Lebanon governor Malek Abdel-Khaleq issued a circular on Monday to all municipalities in South Lebanon, ordering them to carry out a comprehensive survey on chicken- and poultry farms to adopt necessary measures to stop the spread of avian flu.  </Para><Para>Results of the survey were to be delivered to Abdel-Khaleq by Friday.  </Para><Para>Meanwhile, the Amal Movement's social services bureau held a seminar in cooperation with the Abbassieh municipality, Tyre, about avian flu.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Daily Star Staff  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>