<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060407e2480000b" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060408"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>POLITICS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Annan's representative visits Nabatieh  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- SOUTH LEBANON: UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan's personal representative in Lebanon, Geir Pedersen, paid a visit Friday to the southern region of Nabatieh, in an effort to study the south's situation and kick off appropriate developmental programs.  </Para><Para>The residents of the area informed Pedersen of their suffering following the Israeli invasion and continued attacks. They also asked that the UN hand over maps of mines planted by Israel in their land, as well as give them priority in terms of services and contributions to educational, cultural and environmental projects.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>The first stop on Pedersen's visit was the Grand Serail, where he met with the region's governor, Mahmoud Mawla, as well as Nabatieh Mayor, chairman of the Confederation of Municipalities Unions, and a number of the region's mayors.  </Para><Para>Mawla praised Pedersen's visit. In turn, Pedersen said: "This visit is free of any political aspect, it is the first to Nabatieh and will be followed by many other visits." He added: "We will study the projects being presented with the UN development fund."  </Para><Para>Pedersen further said that the UN is cooperating with the Lebanese leadership to preserve "calm" along the southern borders and is urging Israel to halt its violations of Lebanon's airspace. He also said he hoped a calm atmosphere would continue to "allow the participants in the national dialogue to achieve their goals."  </Para><Para>Pedersen also met with MP Ali Bazzi at his residence in Kfarjoz.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Mohammed Zaatari  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>