<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="DSTAR00020060406e2470000h" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060407"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>POLITICS</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Chinese prepare for UNIFIL role  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Beirut -- SOUTH LEBANON: A Chinese battalion has reported for duty in the South and will soon replace a Ukranian unit with the United Nations Interim Forces in Lebanon (UNIFIL). Around 100 Ukranian officers and enlisted personnel have already left Lebanon and will soon be followed by another 100. An official handover ceremony will be held on Sunday in the village of Hinyeh near Tyre.  </Para><Para>The Daily Star went to Hinyeh, where the Chinese camp is located, but was prevented from taking photographs or speaking to the new arrivals.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>However, Chinese troops could be seen moving along the coastal road between Hinyeh and Naqoura, where the headquarters of UNIFIL is located.  </Para><Para>Locals in the area welcomed the new forces, with one man commenting: "Everything has become Chinese: clothes, toys, fireworks and even UNIFIL!"  </Para><Para>The Ukrainian battalion first arrived in the South in July 2000 and has worked on demining the region, notably along the border with Israel. It has also built numerous advanced emergency posts and offered medical and social contributions to the community.  </Para><Para>The Chinese battalion will take over the same duties in terms of logistic and demining.  </Para><Para>UNIFIL was established in 1978 following the Israeli invasion of Lebanon and spread its forces to implement UN Security Council Resolution 425 after the Israeli withdrew in 2000.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Mohammed Zaatari  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 THE DAILY STAR, BEIRUT, LEBANON.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>