<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="FINP000020060404e2440001t" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060404"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>World</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Iran's new 'front line' keeps watch on Israel: Nuclear crisis deepens: Nation accused of using Hezbollah to spy on neighbour  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>ON THE ISRAEL-LEBANON BORDER - Iran has set up a sophisticated intelligence gathering operation in southern Lebanon to identify targets in northern Israel in the event of a military confrontation over its nuclear program.  </Para><Para>Senior Israeli military commanders say Iran has spent tens of millions of dollars helping close ally Hezbollah, the Shiite Muslim group that controls southern Lebanon, to set up a network of control towers and monitoring stations along the entire length of Israel's border with south Lebanon.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Some of the new control towers, which are made of reinforced concrete and fitted with bulletproof reflective glass, are less than 100 metres from Israeli army positions and are clearly visible for long stretches along the border.  </Para><Para>"This is now Iran's front line with Israel," a senior Israeli military commander said.  </Para><Para>"The Iranians are using Hezbollah to spy on us so that they can collect information for future attacks and there is very little we can do about it."  </Para><Para>The Israeli military has reported a significant increase in Hezbollah activity in southern Lebanon since Syria came under intense international pressure to withdraw its forces from the area last year after the assassination of former Lebanese prime minister Rafik Hariri.  </Para><Para>Israeli military officers say teams of Iran's Revolutionary Guards travel regularly to southern Lebanon to help train local Hezbollah fighters in terrorist tactics.  </Para><Para>Tensions between Iran and Israel have intensified dramatically since the election last summer of President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad.  </Para><Para>Israel has repeatedly threatened to take military action to prevent Iran from acquiring nuclear weapons, and the new Iranian government has responded by calling for Israel's destruction.  </Para><Para>Senior Israeli military officers believe Iran is deliberately exploiting the power vacuum caused by Syria's withdrawal to intensify pressure on Israel's northern border.  </Para><Para>Hezbollah is aware that Israel is keen to maintain friendly relations with the new government in Lebanon and believes it can act freely in southern Lebanon without provoking retaliatory strikes from Israel.  </Para><Para>Officers say there has been a sharp increase in border incidents between Hezbollah fighters and Israeli units.  </Para><Para>The main flashpoints are the disputed Druze village of Ghajar, which is divided by the border, and Mount Dov, which Hezbollah also claims should be part of Lebanon.  </Para><Para>The situation is now regarded as so serious many senior Israeli officers openly admit they miss Syria's restraining influence over Hezbollah.  </Para><Para>"When the Syrians were in Lebanon, it was easy for us to control Hezbollah," said an officer.  </Para><Para>"If things got too tense, we could put pressure on Damascus and the Syrians would act quickly to calm things down."  </Para><Para>Although the Lebanese government technically controls the border area, its military is not considered strong enough to control Hezbollah, which takes its orders directly from Tehran.  </Para><Para>"Iran is playing a very dangerous game of cat and mouse on our northern border and it could easily spiral out of control at any moment," said the officer.  </Para><Para>In recent weeks Hezbollah sent unmanned aircraft on reconnaissance missions over the border to photograph sensitive Israeli military installations.  </Para><Para>The spy planes returned to base before being detected by air defence systems.  </Para><Para>In addition to providing intelligence-gathering and communications equipment, Iran has also equipped Hezbollah with improved weapons and ammunition to launch attacks against Israel, including heavy mortars and rockets with a range of up to 45 kilometres.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Con Coughlin  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'>The Daily Telegraph  </Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'>Colour Photo: Mokhtar Al Haj, Reuters / Israeli military
commanders say Iran is setting up a network of monitoring stations
along Israel's entire border with Lebanon.  </Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 National Post . All Rights Reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>