<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="FSII000020060402e24200034" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060402"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Caspar Weinberger  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>CASPAR Weinberger, who died last Tuesday aged 88, was US secretary of defence under President Ronald Reagan from 1981 to 1987.  </Para><Para>Caspar Willard Weinberger was born in San Francisco on August 18, 1917, the son of a lawyer. As a child he was precociously interested in politics; as an adolescent he enjoyed reading records of congressional debates. He studied law at Harvard and then joined the US army. During the Second World War, he served as a member of General Douglas MacArthur's intelligence staff. Returning to California, Weinberger served as a clerk in the federal appeals court before joining a San Francisco law firm. He won election to the California state assembly in 1952 and became chairman of the California Republican Party in 1962. Governor Ronald Reagan appointed him state director of finance in 1968. He served until 1970, when President Richard Nixon appointed him chairman of the Federal Trade Commission. He was named director of the Office of Management and Budget in 1972.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>A self-declared 'fiscal puritan', Weinberger showed a zeal for budget-slashing that earned him the nickname 'Cap the Knife'. He was largely responsible for Nixon's austere 1974 budget which achieved economies by dismantling many of the Great Society programmes initiated by President Johnson. In 1972, Nixon had moved Weinberger to health, education and welfare, the home of many of the doomed programmes, to act (it was said) as a "warm, sympathetic, understanding axe-man". He continued under Gerald Ford until resigning to go into business in 1975.  </Para><Para>Despite his reputation as a cost-cutter, after Reagan appointed him secretary of defence in 1981, Weinberger became a vigorous advocate of the president's plan to boost the defence budget. He established excellent relationships with the leaders of the military services, which were no doubt furthered by his success in securing large appropriations. When Argentina invaded the Falklands in April 1982, Weinberger came down strongly on Britain's side, saying that America could not put a Nato ally and long-standing friend on the same level as Argentina. America went on to provide missiles, aircraft fuel, military equipment, and intelligence information to the British government. America's support helped to cement a close alliance between Reagan and Mrs Thatcher, and in 1988 Weinberger was given an honorary knighthood.  </Para><Para>Weinberger also played a key role in developing a plan to revitalise America's strategic nuclear deterrent, announced by Reagan in 1981. The plan included development of a Stealth aircraft and the deployment of the MX missile. The emergence of the Strategic Defence Initiative, nicknamed 'Star Wars', raised the possibility of a profound change in arms-control negotiations between America and the Soviet Union, but in May 1987 the senate voted to prohibit testing.  </Para><Para>In 1982, Weinberger opposed the contribution of American troops to a multinational force to supervise the departure of the Palestine Liberation Organisation (PLO) from Beirut after the Israeli invasion of Lebanon, on the grounds that no vital American interests were at stake. In contrast, Weinberger strongly supported intervention in Grenada, where turmoil had broken out in 1983 following the overthrow of the government by a pro-Soviet radical group that appeared to threaten 600 American medical students. Since Grenada was a Commonwealth member, the invasion severely tested the UK-US 'special relationship', but the friendship built up during the Falklands crisis ensured that Mrs Thatcher later conceded the operation's success.  </Para><Para>Weinberger also had to call on the 'special relationship' in dealing with the Libyan leader Colonel Gaddafi who, in 1981, laid claim to the Gulf of Sidra, off Libya's coast. In August 1981, two US navy planes shot down two Libyan fighters; in March 1986 Gaddafi fired missiles at American planes in the Gulf, but missed.  </Para><Para>The next month a terrorist bomb exploded in a discotheque in West Berlin, killing two people, including an American serviceman, and injuring 230 others, among them 50 American military personnel. The Americans blamed Gaddafi and decided to take action. On April 15 American F-111s flying from bases in England hit pre-selected targets.  </Para><Para>In 1986 it was disclosed that members of the US administration had continued to support the Contras in Nicaragua after Congress had officially cut off military aid, and that they had raised the money by selling arms to Iran in the hope of securing the release of American hostages held there. Weinberger claimed he had opposed providing arms to Iran and that he did not know proceeds from the sales were going to the Contras, although he had agreed to a sale by the defence department of arms to the CIA, which the CIA then transferred to Iran through Israel.  </Para><Para>When Weinberger resigned in 1987, he cited his wife's declining health as the reason, but it is more likely that the Iran/Contra hearingshad as much to do with his decision. Weinberger was indicted on felony charges of lying to the FBI stemming from the investigations into the Iran/Contra affair, though in 1992 he was given an official pardon by President George HW Bush. After leaving the Pentagon, Weinberger became publisher of Forbesmagazine, where over the next decade he wrote on defence issues.  </Para><Para>Caspar Weinberger married Jane Dalton in 1942. They had a son and a daughter.  </Para><Para>©Telegraph  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>1590955  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c) 2006 Independent Newspapers Ireland Ltd
  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>