<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="JPST000020060406e2450005p" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060405"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><SectionName index='field' fid='se'>Features</SectionName><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>From Our Archives  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>50 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 5, 1956, The Jerusalem Post reported that after protracted deliberations the UN Security Council voted unanimously to send UN Secretary-General Dag Hammarskjold to the Middle East to study the tense situation on Israel's borders and to pursue the prospects of peace in the area.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>The UN Mixed Israeli-Jordanian Armistice Commission, meeting in Wadi Ara, blamed Jordan for a series of infiltration activities into Israel and called on both countries to preserve peace.  </Para><Para>Three soldiers were killed when an Israeli patrol was attacked, close to Kissufim. Uri Gretsman, the Israeli soldier killed a day earlier, was buried.  </Para><Para>The British press accused the US of failing to support their vital interests in the Middle East. The right-wing Daily Mail in an outspoken editorial accused the US of working with the Soviet Union against Britain in Egypt, Jordan and Iraq.  </Para><Para>25 YEARS AGO  </Para><Para>On April 5, 1981, The Jerusalem Post reported that Arab terrorists in South Lebanon shelled Galilee. In Beirut, the Syrian and Lebanese armies clashed in an artillery duel along the Muslim- Christian dividing line, threatening to plunge the whole of Lebanon into a new round of a civil war.  </Para><Para>A 10-day seminar held jointly by the Ben-Gurion University of the Negev and the University of California claimed that the entire Negev was in a grave danger as a free and indiscriminate dumping ground for the local military bases and industrial waste.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'>Alexander Zvielli  </Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>Copyright (c) 2006 Bell &amp; Howell Information and Learning Company. All rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>