<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="MENATW0020060403e24300001" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060403"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'> After almost a month of discussions Lebanon's politicians have still to reach consensus on several pending issues.  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>The National Dialogue is set to commence its fifth round today; amidst droughts of reaching consensus on key issues.  </Para><Para>Following the efforts made by Parliamentary Speaker Nabih Berri, prominent Lebanese leaders began a National Dialogue, around a month back, to discuss their differences and sort out the political stalemate.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>Around 35 prominent leaders, representing 14 groups, including Muslim and Christian, pro and anti-Syrian factions are participating in the National Dialogue. The participants include PM Fouad Siniora, Berri, senior political leaders including Chouf MP Walid Jumblatt, Future Movement MP Saad Hariri, Hizbullah's Chief Sayyed Hassan Nasrallah, Lebanese Forces leader Samir Geagea, former President Amin Gemayel, Free Patriotic Movement leader Kesrouan MP Michel Aoun, a representative from the coalition of Armenian parties, etc.  </Para><Para>The National Dialogue met with some initial success. At the end of the second round of the National Dialogue politicians managed to reach consensus on some hotly debated political issues. The decision was unanimous on announcing that the Shebaa Farms and Kfar Shouba territory belongs to Lebanon. Politicians also agreed to establish diplomatic relations with Syria and further decided to disarm Palestinian factions outside refugee camps. The Palestinian arms will be regulated over the next six months. The Shebaa Farms and Kfar Shouba areas are currently occupied by Israel. While Lebanon claims these areas to be its territory, the UN has said that this is Syrian area, occupied by Israel. On the issue of relations with Syria, participants to the National Dialogue said that diplomatic relations between Lebanon and Syria would be as equals, both countries would establish diplomatic relations and embassies, as well as clearly mark the border between the two countries.  </Para><Para>However, no consensus has been reached, so far, on the issues regarding disarming Hizbullah, as well as on the issue of resignation of President Emile Lahoud.  </Para><Para>Last week's incidents point out that the solutions to these two vexing issues may not be very easy. Last week's fourth round ended in a few hours without any major discussions and was postponed to today in view of the Arab summit, which was held in Khartoum, last week.  </Para><Para>Last week in Khartoum PM Faoud Siniora and Lahoud, both attending the Arab summit, clashed with each other - at the international forum. Both leaders disagreed in their views during the summit. Siniora reportedly asked for the removal of a clause pledging support to the armed Lebanese resistance.  </Para><Para>Later this week Lahoud again had a bitter exchange of words with March 14 ministers at the cabinet meeting. Lahoud and the ministers traded insults and ridiculed each other. This was followed by a walkout on the part of the March 14 ministers. The heated debate commenced after a verbal clash between Telecommunications Minister Marwan Hamade and Lahoud.  </Para><Para>The positive sign is that despite the increased political rhetoric and last week's political feud all parties have indicated keenness to continue with the dialogue and are scheduled to commence the fifth round of discussions. The negative is that the tougher political postures adopted by different parties might act as a hindrance to arriving at an early consensus.  </Para><Para>While, the politicians resolve their stand the economy continues to remain in state of limbo. Key economic decisions and the fate of the Beirut donor's conference continues to get delayed; increasing Lebanon's unacceptably and almost unmanageable high public debt of USD 36bn; around 180% of GDP.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'></Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(c)Copyright 2006. Internet Securities, Inc. All rights reserved  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>