<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="MEWGUN0020060403e2430000c" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060403"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Gulf News: Is peace in the Middle East a small step nearer?.  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>Ehud Olmert, leader of Kadima, the largest party in the 17th Knesset, will soon be heading for Washington at President George W. Bush's invitation for the ritual visit of an incoming Israeli prime minister.  </Para><Para>What Bush tells him will be of vital importance for the future of the Middle East but also for that of the United States as well. It is not clear, however, that Bush has grasped that if Israel is to live in security, and if the US is to tame the dangerous groundswell of anger at its policies in the Arab and Muslim world, then an Israeli-Palestinian peace is an absolute priority.  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para>What are the chances of a breakthrough? The auguries are not particularly promising. Olmert, now busy putting together a government coalition, will no doubt repeat in Washington his mantra that there is no "peace partner" on the Palestinian side a cynical myth which Israel has invoked for years as a pretext for avoiding negotiations. He will continue to call for the boycott of Hamas, demonised as a "terrorist organisation", although it won January's democratic elections in the occupied territories and has now formed the new Palestinian government.  </Para><Para>Above all, Olmert will seek American support for new Israeli boundaries, deep in the West Bank, which he wants to impose unilaterally. Speaking in Berlin last week, US Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice was rash enough to say the United States might indeed back a unilateral Israeli withdrawal from the West Bank. She would have been wise to be more cautious.  </Para><Para>Bad counsellers  </Para><Para>The US and Israel have been notoriously bad counsellers of each other. The US accepted and funded Israel's 22-year occupation of southern Lebanon from 1978 to 2000, as well as its ongoing illegal colonisation of Palestinian territories policies which have radicalised Arab and Muslim opinion and led to the rise of militant organisations such as Hezbollah and Hamas, not to mention Al Qaida.  </Para><Para>Israel, in turn, and its friends in the United States, lobbied, intrigued and pressed the US to attack Iraq in 2003, with the catastrophic consequences for the US and the region that are now plain for all to see.  </Para><Para>There are, however, one or two shafts of light in an otherwise gloomy scene. The Israeli elections of March 28 resulted in the striking defeat of Likud and of the national-religious bloc as a whole, diehard advocates of territorial expansion, and a clear shift of Israeli opinion to the more moderate centre-left. Potentially, this could provide the political basis for an acceptable settlement. In a Knesset of 120 members, Olmert is widely expected to form a coalition consisting of his own Kadima party (29 seats); Amir Peretz's Labour party (20), the newly-formed old people's Pensioners Party (7), the ultra-orthodox Shas (12) and the largely working class Mizrahi party (13). Together, these parties would form a strong parliamentary bloc, which would also have the support of the far-left Meretz (4) and of the Arab parties (10).  </Para><Para>But to succeed even with such a strong coalition, Olmert would need to show both courage and vision. He needs to go well beyond the programme he announced during his election campaign. Unilaterally-imposed borders will neither bring Israel peace and security, nor will they be internationally recognised. Attempts by Israel to hold East Jerusalem, the Jordan Valley and large colonies such as Ariel, which intrudes some 21 kilometres inside the West Bank, would not be acceptable to the Palestinians and are bound to be violently contested.  </Para><Para>If Olmert were a statesman, he would invite the new Palestinian Prime Minister, Esmail Haniya, to Occupied Jerusalem and open immediate final status negotiations. In the meantime, however, Hamas needs urgently to explain to the world where it stands on key questions of war and peace, borders, and violence. Haniya has already declared that his government would make "all possible efforts to reach a just peace that ends occupation and restores rights to the Palestinians. We have never been advocates of war, terrorism or bloodshed."  </Para><Para>The problem is that he has not been heard. Hamas is still routinely depicted as "anti-peace", as committed to armed struggle and as wanting to recover not just the occupied territories but the whole of former Palestine. It needs to convince the Israelis, and the international community, that it is potentially the best "peace partner" Israel could hope to have, because it alone could make peace stick and it alone could discipline other violent factions.  </Para><Para>Moreover, since it represents Palestinian national aspirations, it is well suited to create the viable, independent, democratic Palestinian state on Israel's borders, which would be the best guarantee of the long-term security of the Jewish state.  </Para><Para>But are the US and Israel listening?  </Para><Para>Patrick Seale is a commentator and author  </Para><Para>of several books on Middle East affairs.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>WGNS48113633  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>The Financial Times Limited. Asia Africa Intelligence Wire. All material subject to copyright. Gulf News © 2006 All rights reserved.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>