<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="RSKW000020060408e2470000a" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060407"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Iran risk: Political stability risk  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>COUNTRY BRIEFING  </Para><Para>FROM THE ECONOMIST INTELLIGENCE UNIT  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para display='asis'>RISK RATINGS             Current Current Previous Previous
                         Rating  Score   Rating   Score
Overall assessment       D       67      D        67
Political stability risk D       80      D        80
Note: E=most risky; 100=most risky.
  </Para><Para>SUMMARY  </Para><Para>The conservatives are entrenched within the state's powerful unelected institutions. Popular disillusionment with the ability of the political system to effect widely demanded liberalisation has grown significantly. This may induce some activists to pursue more direct means to effect change, such as civil disobedience. However, weariness seems apparent in equal measure, and a widespread uprising appears highly unlikely. The US is supporting measures to assist regime change in Iran, and the likelihood of multilateral economic sanctions being applied has risen, primarily due to Iran's failure to allay concerns over its nuclear activities. In addition, Iranian interference in Iraq is likely to further antagonise the US. However there could be a lessening of tensions if proposed direct Iranian talks with the US on Iraq make any progress.  </Para><Para>SCENARIOS  </Para><Para>The dispute over Iran's nuclear programme escalates sufficiently to cause a split among Iranian powerbrokers (Moderate Risk)  </Para><Para>Despite a pledge made in late 2003 (and repeated in November 2004) to improve transparency over its nuclear activities, Iran’s interaction with the inspectors of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) has been characterised by slow and piecemeal co-operation. Iran has followed through on longstanding threats to resume aspects of its drive to develop the nuclear fuel cycle, by resuming uranium conversion (an early stage in the fuel cycle) in August last year and enrichment-related research in January 2006. It suspended such activities “voluntarily” under agreements with European intermediaries (Iran blames unfulfilled promises on the part of the Europeans, above all their insistence Iran gives up its fuel cycle activities). With Iran having been reported to the UN Security Council (UNSC), the possibility that sanctions may eventually be imposed has increased. Tough embargoes seem unlikely, but the issue seems certain to escalate at least in the near term and the possibility that the US or Israel may ultimately take military action has increased. As pressure mounts on Iran, so will the possibility of disagreements emerging within the ruling elite in Iran between those insisting on a firm line and others pressing for less confrontational stance. If such a dispute spread to the armed forces, it could lead to instability. Expatriates should make contingency plans to leave the country rapidly.  </Para><Para>Developments in Iraq add to tensions between Iran and the US (Moderate Risk)  </Para><Para>The links between Iran and a number of armed militias in Iraq has caused tensions since the fall of the former regime of Saddam Hussein in 2003. Allegations of Iran's role in improving the military capability of Iraqi groups opposed to the coalition presence, and the presence of Iranian intelligence officers in Iraq, has raised disputes between Iran and the US. Developments on the ground in Iraq could intensify tension in the future, which could overlap with disputes over Iran's alleged nuclear weapons programme. Given Iraq's fragility, and Iran's influence over a number of key Shia trends in what is liable to be the leading political grouping in the new Iraqi government, there is a strong possibility that Iran and the US will hold direct talks on Iraq in the medium term. But the narrow basis for any US-Iranian understanding, in part given the US's determination to "ring fence” any discussion, may limit substantive progress. On the other hand, the simple fact of being willing to sit down together, in what would be the first time such talks have been conducted on a public basis since diplomatic relations were broken over more than 25 years ago, could serve to lessen tensions between Iran and the US.  </Para><Para>The conservatives tighten political and social restrictions, prompting a backlash from reformist activists (Moderate Risk)  </Para><Para>The conservatives’ victory in disputed parliamentary elections in February 2004 and the election of the conservative Mahmoud Ahmadinejad in presidential polls in June 2005 dashed hopes of political and social liberalisation in the near term and may result in the reversal of the modest political and social gains made by the previous legislature and administration. Some activists may turn to more direct methods to effect change such as civil disobedience, possibly even violence. The risk of clashes between students, the most vocal advocates of reform, and militia who support the conservatives remains. It appears unlikely, though, that students would be able to prompt a wider uprising; militia loyal to the conservative establishment have in the past had little difficulty putting down protests--using a degree of brutality as a deterrent for future activity. Besides this, there is no obvious leader around whom a movement could coalesce, and the wider appetite for revolution--although extremely difficult to gauge--is by no means apparent. However, a wider mobilisation remains an outside possibility, particularly if the US decided to intervene more directly in Iran. Expatriates should have regular and candid talks with local staff. Business people should also avoid areas where protests are known to be occurring. Foreigners should make contingency plans to leave the country rapidly.  </Para><Para>BACKGROUND  </Para><Para>(Background material is updated twice yearly. Last update: May 5th, 2005)  </Para><Para>Political Forces  </Para><Para>Iran has a dual power structure, with a supreme religious leader (the vali-e faqih) and a president. Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, who came to power in 1989 after the death of the founder of the Islamic Republic of Iran, Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, holds the highest religious office. Mohammed Khatami was re-elected president for a second four-year term in June 2001. The most recent election for the Iranian parliament (Majlis) was held in February 2004. Political parties, banned since 1985, are now permitted to present candidates at elections, although they remain loose organisations.  </Para><Para>Legitimate political activity is permitted only among those who publicly accept the velayat-e faqih (rule of the supreme Islamic jurisprudent). Political parties, legalised in 1998 after a 13-year ban, are still at an early stage of development and policy formation, and party discipline is inconsistent. Nevertheless, factions within the ruling hierarchy, and in the Majlis, are clear. Although these have often been defined broadly as “reformist” or “conservative”, the system is fluid and a range of political allegiances exist based on patronage, specific interests and the exchange of favours. Mr Khatami’s government had to lobby strongly to move legislation even through the reformist-dominated Majlis, and its policies were frequently subject to complication or even reversal in the face of political maneuvering or popular opposition. Since Mr Khatami was first elected in 1997, the Servants of Construction, the Assembly of the Militant Clergy, the Islamic Participation Front and the Crusaders of the Islamic Revolution have become well-established groups closely associated with the reformist camp. The conservative camp has been focused around the Society for Militant Clergy, the Allied Islamic Society and Society of the Qom Seminary Teachers. Candidates who stood for the Abadgaran bloc in the 2004 elections were closely connected to the Office of the Supreme Leader, and this affiliation seems likely to override others in importance in the 2004-08 Majlis. The Abadgaran-dominated Majlis has essentially blocked Mr Khatami’s legislative programme--and in some cases reversed it.  </Para><Para>Main political figures  </Para><Para>Ayatollah Seyyed Ali Khamenei: Vali-e faqih (supreme Islamic jurisprudent, or supreme leader) since Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini’s death in 1989, Ayatollah Khamenei in effect holds the post for life. As pressure for political and economic reform developed in the 1990s, Ayatollah Khamenei at first provided an effective bridge between conservative and reformist figures. As the reformists gained control of the government and parliament, however, and the power struggle began to intensify, this bridging role proved increasingly untenable. Although he intervened on occasion to restrain the judiciary over particularly contentious issues, he generally tended to back the conservative camp. This reflected his own need to maintain the support of conservative seminaries, where his poor religious qualifications limit his personal standing. He remained silent in the face of anti-democratic actions taken by the judiciary and conservative-dominated Guardian Council, while sometimes intervening directly to quash reformist initiatives. As his own authority rests on religious, rather than democratic, claims to power, he also showed great reluctance to support the attempts by the president, Mohammed Khatami, to restore real authority to the presidency and parliament. As head of the armed forces, judiciary and a range of other bodies, Ayatollah Khamenei’s behind-the-scenes influence is considerable, although he has generally limited his overt interventions in political affairs to strategic, rather than day-to-day, issues, notably where foreign policy decisions are concerned. Questions have long been raised over Ayatollah Khamenei’s health, with rumours suggesting he is suffering from cancer continuing to circulate in Tehran.  </Para><Para>Mohammed Khatami: Mr Khatami, whose second and final four-year term in office ends in mid-2005, has sought to liberalise the Islamic Republic’s social norms and political structure with a view to strengthening its institutions and support base. Fluent in Arabic, German and English, he initially oversaw a considerable improvement in Iran’s relations with the Arab world and Europe--although the process has been interrupted, since late 2002, by an intensifying dispute over Iran’s nuclear ambitions. A lifelong devotee of the Islamic Republic (he is a cleric, holding the rank of hojjatolislam), as well as a dedicated supporter of reform, Mr Khatami has spent his period in office seeking to implement change cautiously and through consensus. The failure of this approach cost him support, however, and his reluctance to take a principled stand against his opponents by following through on his threats to resign undermined his standing and credibility. His administration has suffered a number of legislative reverses since the conservative-dominated Majlis took office in May 2004.  </Para><Para>Hojatoleslam Ali Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani: A consummate political fixer, Mr Rafsanjani has managed to remain at the centre of Iranian politics since the revolution. He served as Majlis speaker under Ayatollah Khomeini before winning the presidency in 1989. An economic reform programme began promisingly, allowing him to renew his presidential mandate in 1993, but parliamentary opposition, combined with the impact of US sanctions on Iran, prevented more radical reform. In August 1997 he became chairman of the Expediency Council, a body that arbitrates disputes between the Majlis and the Guardian Council. Widely regarded as having exploited for his own ends the offices he has held, he has seen his popular standing fall and was humiliated when he failed to win a Majlis seat during the first round of the 2000 election. He subsequently withdrew from the poll, but his wealth, connections and control of the Expediency Council meant that he remained a crucial player behind the scenes. Alarmed by the radical stance of the conservative-dominated Majlis, he is considering standing for the presidency once more in the June 2005 election.  </Para><Para>Hassan Rohani: Head of the Supreme National Security Council, a body established in 1989 with a broad mandate to safeguard national interests and protect the Islamic revolution, he shot to prominence in 2003 as the point man for international diplomacy related to Iran's nuclear programme. His sound revolutionary credentials--he was active from an early age in efforts to overthrow the shah, and was arrested twice for his pains--and his good relations with both Ayatollah Khamenei and Mr Rafsanjani have prompted speculation that he may become Iran’s next president.  </Para><Para>Mohammed Reza Khatami: As the younger brother of the president and head of the Participation Front, Iran’s largest reformist party, Mohammed Reza rapidly became one of the more vocal proponents of social and political change in Iran. He had been seen as a possible presidential candidate for the reformist movement following Mr Khatami's second and final term in office. However, his increasingly strident criticism of the leadership earned him the wrath of hardliners and he was disqualified from standing in the February 2004 parliamentary election. Although now without public office, he is likely to remain a key figure in efforts by the reformists to re-establish political momentum.  </Para><Para>The clergy: Islamic Iran is a theocracy embodied in the principle of velayat-e faqih, and the clergy enjoy tremendous power. Since the revolution, almost all important posts have been occupied by senior clerics. Historically, the clergy have always been at the centre of Iranian society and an important source of spiritual guidance to the population. They are by no means an homogenous group, however, with divisions readily apparent between pro-reform figures (such as Mr Khatami), moderates and more hardline elements.  </Para><Para>The bazaar: A peculiarly Iranian feature of the political and economic scene, the bazaar refers to Iran’s traditional import-export merchants, who wield considerable influence over economic policy. They showed their power in 1978 by calling a series of strikes, paralysing Iran’s economy and hastening the departure of the shah. Since the revolution, the bazaaris have enjoyed a close relationship with the Islamic regime, benefiting from lucrative business contracts in exchange for funding individual mosques and conservative candidates for public office.  </Para><Para>The bonyad: The bonyad (Islamic charitable foundations) were created after the revolution and given control of the extensive commercial holdings of the shah and his close allies. They were charged with running these interests to provide welfare for the poor, but have vast multibillion-dollar conglomerates controlling large swathes of the Iranian economy. Dominated by conservatives, the bonyad enjoy a range of privileges that have allowed them to consolidate their hold over the non-oil economy. The larger bonyad, such as the Bonyad-e Mostazafan va Janbazan (Foundation of the Oppressed), are estimated to control US$12bn in assets and employ some 400,000 workers through the enterprises and properties they own. Mr Khatami’s administration has made some effort to rein them in, but the reassertion of full conservative political control will ensure they remain economically dominant and politically influential.  </Para><Para>Political Development  </Para><Para>Struggle for reform  </Para><Para>Since Ayatollah Khomeini’s death Iran’s domestic politics have evolved into an increasingly bitter power struggle between conservatives and reformists within the regime. From 1989 to 1997 Mr Rafsanjani sought to implement a programme of gradual economic and political reform, but his more conservative rivals frequently blocked his policies. However, the conservatives lost their absolute majority in parliament in the 1996 election, and an avowedly reformist candidate, Mr Khatami, shocked the conservative establishment in 1997 by winning a landslide victory in the presidential election. Mr Khatami’s supporters then defeated conservatives in the parliamentary election held in 2000, gaining majority control.  </Para><Para>The election marked the start of a concerted backlash by the conservative clerical establishment. Hardliners, alarmed by the reformists’ growing strength, used their positions within the judiciary and the state’s other powerful unelected institutions (primarily the Guardian Council--a conservative vetting body) to mount a vigorous campaign. Scores of Mr Khatami's supporters, including ministers, senior officials, journalists, student leaders and clerics, were tried on political charges and imprisoned or forced from office. The courts closed scores of pro-reform newspapers and journals. In mid-1999 two students were killed and many were injured during several days of nationwide protests by pro-reform activists that were forcefully suppressed by the security forces.  </Para><Para>Frustration builds  </Para><Para>Despite the harassment and limited achievements during his first term in office, Mr Khatami stood for a second four-year term in June 2001, winning a resounding victory that underscored the popular desire for political and institutional reform in Iran. However, the scale of the president’s support far from cowed his opponents, who, if anything, intensified their campaign. Between 2000 and early 2004, the Guardian Council blocked about 100 bills proposed by the reformist-dominated parliament. Crucially, two bills proposed by Mr Khatami in late 2002 that would have strengthened the powers of the presidency at the expense of the Guardian Council and the conservative (and highly politicised) judiciary were repeatedly blocked. Public disillusionment mounted, over both the ability of the political system to deliver change and the willingness of Mr Khatami and his close aides to confront their political opponents directly. Mr Khatami repeatedly hinted that he would resign, but, concerned over the implications for domestic stability, failed to follow through on these threats.  </Para><Para>The conservatives win control of parliament  </Para><Para>In February 2003, amid extremely low turnout, conservative candidates registered sweeping gains vis-a-vis the reformists in municipal elections. Many voters who had previously backed the reformists stayed away, handing victory to the conservatives, whose support base is more dedicated. Sensing the opportunity to deal a decisive blow to Mr Khatami's movement, the Guardian Council vetoed some 2,500 of the 8,200 candidates for the February 2004 parliamentary election. Nearly all of the disqualified candidates were reformists, including more than 80 sitting MPs, among them the president's brother Mohammed Reza Khatami. The conservative Abadgaran Iran-e Islami (Developers of an Islamic Iran) bloc won about 195 of the 290 seats; the reformist representation fell to about 50 seats from about 200 in the previous parliament. The election marked the end of the reformist movement in its current guise, and left the cabinet with no real possibility of advancing its legislative agenda before the expiry of Mr Khatami’s second and final term in office in June 2005. So disillusioned had the electorate become with the ability of the political system to deliver change that the conservatives may even have prevailed in the absence of disqualifications. The reformists had become deeply tainted in the eyes of the electorate by their participation in--and therefore endorsement of--a political system that appeared unable to effect change.  </Para><Para>Abadagaran’s radicalness splits the conservatives  </Para><Para>Abadgaran, which is close to the supreme leader and made up largely of previously unknown technocrats and former members of the Revolutionary Guard, was created as a staunchly conservative movement to counter the reformists--unpopular “old guard” figures stepped aside to allow its members to stand in the election. However, expectations among many centrist conservatives that it would be compliant were quickly dispelled as parliament proved to be radical and assertive, adopting populist, nationalist economic policies and an uncompromising stance on international issues, primarily the vexed question of Iran’s nuclear programme. Parliament’s policies alarmed many centrist conservatives, including Mr Rafsanjani who in early 2005 was considering standing for the presidency again in order to counter the Majlis’s radical agenda. Mr Rafsanjani lacks popular standing, being widely considered to have exploited the offices he has held to his own ends, and seems unlikely to stand unless his victory is at least likely--which is dependent on winning the approval of the supreme leader. Mr Rafsanjani has successfully sought accommodation with the supreme leader in the past, but Ayatollah Khamenei’s support cannot be guaranteed as it will threaten the concentration of power in the hands of hardline forces--Abadgaran, the Revolutionary Guard and the Guardian Council--which have enjoyed the supreme leader’s support. If Mr Rafsanjani does not prevail, the election will probably be won by a conservative close to Ayatollah Khamenei, most likely the former head of state television, Ali Larijani, although the outcome is highly uncertain and the possibility that another candidate may yet triumph cannot be ruled out.  </Para><Para>Important recent events  </Para><Para>May 1997: Mohammed Khatami easily defeats the conservative speaker of the Majlis (parliament), Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri, in the presidential election, taking 70% of the vote. Ayatollah Ali Khamenei appoints Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani as chairman of the Expediency Council.  </Para><Para>July 1999: Two pro-reform students are killed during a police raid on a Tehran university dormitory, prompting nationwide protests and further clashes between students and the security forces.  </Para><Para>February 2000: Mr Khatami’s camp wins a landslide victory in the sixth parliamentary election.  </Para><Para>June 2001: Conservatives fail to field a strong candidate in the presidential election, allowing Mr Khatami to raise his margin of victory and take 77% of the vote.  </Para><Para>August 2001: The Iran-Libya Sanctions Act (ILSA), first passed in 1996, is renewed for a further five ye ars, threatening the US interests of non-US firms that invest in the development of Iran’s oil industry.  </Para><Para>September 2001: Iran condemns the September 11th attacks on the US, but also criticises US retaliatory attacks on Afghanistan. Behind the scenes it is less confrontational, and Iran facilitates the creation of a post-Taliban Afghan government, earning plaudits from the EU. No improvement in US ties accrues, however, and in February 2002 the US names Iran as one of three states constituting an “axis of evil”.  </Para><Para>August 2002: Mr Khatami introduces legislation designed to strengthen his authority at the expense of the conservatives. Mr Khatami later fails to follow through on his threat to resign as the laws are rejected, contributing to growing popular disillusionment with the ability of the political system to effect widely demanded change. The National Council of Resistance (the political wing of the Mujahideen-e Khalq, an Iraq-based opposition group listed as a “terrorist” organisation by the US) reveals the existence of two major nuclear fuel-cycle facilities in Iran, prompting concern that Iran may be pursuing a nuclear weapons capability.  </Para><Para>March 2003: The US-led invasion of Iraq causes disquiet in Iranian ruling circles given the obvious hostility towards the Islamic Republic from figures within and connected to the US administration.  </Para><Para>February 2004: Amid sweeping disqualifications of reformist candidates, the conservative Abadgaran bloc wins about 195 of the 290 seats in parliament. The parliament quickly asserts itself, adopting radical, populist economic policies.  </Para><Para>November 2005: Following fraught negotiations, Iran and the EU troika of the UK, France and Germany reach an agreement for Iran to recommit to a “suspension” of its nuclear fuel-cycle activities in return for the EU restarting talks over a trade and co-operation agreement and assisting Iran’s application to join the World Trade Organisation (WTO). The accord allows for talks to begin on a lasting solution to the nuclear issue.  </Para><Para>March 2005: In response to European entreaties, the US finally moves for the first time to offer Iran incentives to give up its fuel-cycle activities, overtly backing the EU talks by agreeing not to prevent Iran from beginning WTO accession talks and by allowing Iran to purchase spare parts for its civil aviation fleet. Iran rejects the offers as the rights of any normal country.  </Para><Para>International Relations and Defence  </Para><Para>The government’s control of foreign policy is limited  </Para><Para>The election of the moderate Mr Khatami as president in 1997 initially heralded a marked improvement in Iran’s foreign relations. The initiatives that the charismatic leader pursued substantially reduced the suspicion and hostility that had informed Iran’s ties with its neighbours and much of the West throughout the 1980s and much of the 1990s, easing its isolation. Only ties with the US (and Israel) were not warmed by the rapprochement. The failure in this area is symptomatic of the broader limits that the president has faced in his control over policy. In particular, his conservative opponents were able to set the boundaries of foreign policy strategy through their influence vis-a-vis Ayatollah Khamenei, who has the final say on key issues. Hardliners continued to run their own foreign policy on some sensitive issues, such as support for anti-Israeli groups like Hizbullah and Hamas. The president had little authority over policy on these issues, which often ran contrary to the government’s broader foreign policy drive, and this undermined his credibility.  </Para><Para>European ties firm despite US pressure  </Para><Para>Iran's ties with the countries of mainland Europe have never been as politically contentious as its relations with the US and the UK. Trade relations with Germany, France and Italy, as well as Japan, provided the basis for strengthening political links, which Mr Khatami personally endorsed through several visits to Europe. Even ties with the UK strengthened following the election of new governments in both countries in 1997, with the infamous Salman Rushdie issue (in 1989 Ayatollah Khomeini issued a religious edict calling for the death of the UK-based author) largely forgotten. Diplomatic relations were re-established at full ambassadorial level after the Iranian government formally distanced itself from the edict in late 1998, and the UK foreign secretary, Jack Straw, visited Iran three times in 2001-02--the first visits by such a high-ranking UK official since the revolution. Mr Khatami’s re-election in mid-2001 was widely welcomed in Europe, as was the constructive role Europe regarded Iran to have played in the Afghan conflict and the formation of a post-Taliban Afghan government. To formalise, and further enhance, bilateral ties, the EU and Iran agreed in late 2002 to begin negotiations on a trade and co-operation agreement.  </Para><Para>However, relations have since become more contentious. Little progress has been made over long-standing problems such as Iranian backing for militant Islamist groups opposed to Israel and Iran's poor human rights record. Growing concern of European states over the weakness of Mr Khatami's government in the face of the conservative opposition was heightened by the 2004 parliamentary election, which the EU described as “flawed”. The election compounded EU concerns that to conclude a trade and co-operation agreement risks, in effect, legitimising the rule of the hardliners. Potentially by far the most the most serious issue, though, concerns hardening suspicions that the goal of Iran's nuclear programme is to acquire a nuclear weapons capability rather than merely to augment power generation as Iran insists.  </Para><Para>Relations with the US remain very poor  </Para><Para>In his first years in office, Mr Khatami made some tentative moves towards normalising ties with the US, the “great Satan” of Iranian post-revolution political discourse. In 1998, shortly after he came to power, Mr Khatami made a conciliatory address to the US people, aired on CNN. In it, he set the stage for a gradual thawing of attitudes during the first stages of his presidency. This led to academic and sporting exchanges, and small but symbolic shifts in policy. The US decision to rescind its ban on the import of Iranian luxury goods in March 2000 represented the most significant relaxation in the US stance, particularly as it was accompanied by a statement of regret from the then US secretary of state, Madeleine Albright, for past US interference in Iran’s internal affairs.  </Para><Para>Following the election of George W Bush to the US presidency in late 2000, it was initially assumed that the rapprochement between the two states would accelerate. This expectation was buoyed by the close links between the new US government and the US oil industry, which has long complained that sanctions barring its involvement in Iran do little but damage US commercial interests. The steady improvement in ties between Iran and key US allies in the region, including Saudi Arabia, also left US policy towards Iran out of step with the regional mood, and made its claim that Iran represented a threat to regional stability increasingly difficult to defend.  </Para><Para>However, hopes that this would lead to a new and improved phase in ties were misplaced, and far from picking up speed, the tentative rapprochement went firmly into reverse. This was first apparent in August 2001 when US sanctions (The Iran-Libya Sanctions Act) on non-US firms investing in the Iranian oil and gas sector were extended for a further five years. Despite the indirect support that Iran offered the US in its military campaign to unseat the Taliban regime in Afghanistan, Mr Bush, in his 2002 State of the Union address, named Iran (along with Iraq and North Korea) as one part of an “axis of evil” that threatened the US and had to be confronted. Continued US hostility has been based in part on claims that Iran sponsors Islamic “terrorist” groups such as Hizbullah and Hamas, and Iran remains listed by the US State Department as the “most active state sponsor of terror”. Underlying the US stance towards Iran are memories of the storming of the US embassy in Tehran in 1980, together with attacks on US interests in Lebanon in the 1980s and in Saudi Arabia in 1996, which led to heavy loss of US life. The US claims these attacks were organised through Tehran.  </Para><Para>The US-led invasion of Iraq in March 2003 was greeted with ambivalence by the Iranian government: on the one hand, “regime change” in Baghdad would see the welcome end of the rule of Saddam Hussein, who was responsible for launching a war with Iran that claimed more than half a million lives. On the other hand, it was seen as completing the US military encirclement of Iran, leaving the US well-placed to exert pressure on the Islamic Republic. The explicit hostility of some figures within and connected to the US administration even gave rise, however fleetingly, to suspicions that the US may next turn to "regime change" in Tehran.  </Para><Para>Iran's nuclear programme is the key foreign policy issue  </Para><Para>However, by far the most important dispute between Iran and the US--and one that will do much to determine whether co-operation or antagonism prevail in other spheres--is Iran’s nuclear programme. The US has long alleged that, beneath an avowedly civilian programme, Iran has been covertly pursuing a nuclear weapons capability, but broader international concerns have risen markedly from late 2002 as it has emerged that Iran’s programme is far more sophisticated and advanced than had previously been known. The central difficulty is Iran’s stated aim to develop the nuclear fuel cycle for electricity generation. Iran has long been building a nuclear power plant with Russian help at Bushehr on the Gulf coast. Since Iran was due to purchase fuel from Russia to fire the facility, this was deemed a process that could be relatively satisfactorily policed. Concern has mounted, however, as Iran has made it clear that it intends to produce its own fuel and as it has emerged that the necessary facilities are relatively well-developed. This is a different prospect since the facilities used to produce fuel for nuclear power stations can readily be used to produce material for a weapon. Concerns abroad are therefore unlikely to abate unless Iran gives up its fuel-cycle activities.  </Para><Para>International efforts to dissuade Iran from pressing ahead with the fuel cycle have so far foundered. Facing a deadline from the board of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA)--the UN-affiliated body responsible for monitoring members states’ compliance with the 1970 Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT)--to provide greater transparency over its nuclear activities (IAEA inspectors had complained of slow, incomplete and sometimes changing accounts), Iran committed to a “suspension” of uranium-enrichment activities in late 2003, under an agreement forged with the European troika of the UK, France and Germany. The accord fell apart during 2004 amid Iranian accusations that the Europeans were little more than US stooges. With a crisis looming once more, Iran and the EU troika forged another agreement in November 2004 under which Iran committed itself to wider suspension--of all fuel related activities--in return for the EU restarting stalled talks over the trade and co-operation accord and actively supporting Iran’s application to join the World Trade Organisation (WTO). The accord provided for talks to begin to find a lasting solution to the issue. However, it appeared frail. The EU recognised that it was unable to meet its promise over the WTO application against the US’s will and that, crucially, it could not address Iran’s security concerns, which largely focus on the US.  </Para><Para>In March 2005 the US finally acquiesced to EU entreaties and for the first time departed from its “stick only” approach by agreeing to drop its objection to Iran’s accession to the WTO and to allow Iran to purchase spare parts for use in its civil aviation industry, stricken from years of US sanctions. However, Iran dismissed the “incentives” as sovereign rights and has continued to insist its suspension of fuel-cycle activities is “voluntary”--a condition repeatedly recognised by the Europeans. (Indeed, Iran is entirely entitled to develop a nuclear fuel cycle provided its activities are approved by the IAEA.) The issue therefore seems unlikely to be resolved through diplomatic means without fuller engagement between the US and Iran.  </Para><Para>Relations with the Arab world  </Para><Para>Relations with the Arab world in general and the Gulf states in particular were dominated throughout the 1980s by the war with Iraq and concerns over the threat posed to Arab regimes by Iran’s populist Islamic revolution. Since the end of the war, Iran has tried to re-establish its links with the states of the Arabian peninsula, and was helped by Iraq’s 1990 invasion of Kuwait, which effectively demonstrated the threat posed to the region by an unfettered Iraq. Qatar, Kuwait and Oman were the first to move towards Iran, while trade relations with Dubai provided the basis for relations with the UAE, which have strengthened since early 2002, despite the Abu Musa territorial dispute.  </Para><Para>The Abu Musa dispute  </Para><Para>A long-running dispute over three strategic Gulf islands, Abu Musa and the Greater and Lesser Tunbs, resurfaced in 1992, generating tension between Iran and the six-member Gulf Co-operation Council (GCC). In March 1992 Iran turned back a ship carrying passengers from the UAE to Abu Musa, leading the UAE to accuse Iran of annexing the islands, which had been jointly administered by the Iranian government and the emirate of Sharjah since 1971. Iran has offered direct talks with Sharjah, but has rejected the UAE’s call for international arbitration by the International Court of Justice in The Hague. The issue is a constant, if diminishing, irritant in relations between Iran and GCC states.  </Para><Para>Relations with Saudi Arabia  </Para><Para>The biggest prize for Iran has rested in restoring relations with Saudi Arabia, which has long feared Persian hegemony in the Gulf and the threat Iran’s Islamic revolution could pose to stability within Saudi Arabia itself. Feelers first put out by Mr Rafsanjani and developed by Mr Khatami have resulted in closer co-operation over a range of issues, including OPEC policy, regional security concerns and arrangements for the annual haj pilgrimage, which has often been the source of much contention between the two countries. A bilateral “security pact” was signed in 2001 and ties have been supported by the strong personal relationship between Mr Khatami and the crown prince, Abdullah bin Abdel-Aziz al-Saud, of Saudi Arabia. However, although Saudi Arabia has been publicly guarded, the reassertion of control by radical trends, coupled with Iran’s nuclear programme, will have caused concern in Riyadh. Iran’s attempts to improve relations with non-Gulf Arab states such as Egypt and Jordan, with whom ties were severed after the 1979 revolution, have followed the same pattern. In late 2003 Iran and Egypt seem poised to restore full diplomatic relations, with Mr Khatami and the Egyptian president, Hosni Mubarak, meeting in Geneva, the first contact between the heads of state of the two countries since the Islamic revolution, but the breakthrough foundered.  </Para><Para>Relations with Russia  </Para><Para>Russo-Iranian relations have strengthened markedly since the collapse of the Soviet Union, despite US efforts to dissuade Russia from normalising ties. Russia has rewarded Iranian diplomatic and commercial initiatives with continuing support for Iran’s nuclear power programme--despite mounting international concerns over Iran’s ambitions. Russian construction of a reactor at Bushehr is close to completion and in early 2005 an agreement was finally signed for Russia to provide Iran with enriched uranium to fire it. Russia has also agreed to allow Iran to manufacture Russian-designed airliners and anti-tank missiles under licence, while arms deals are reported to have opened the way for the supply of tanks, missiles and submarines direct to the Iranian armed forces. In response, the US has halted aid programmes to several Russian scientific institutes and made clear its strong disapproval of Russian backing for Iran’s nuclear energy and armament programme. For Iran, Russia offers the attractions of political and diplomatic support, military assistance and technology. Iran has worked hard to diffuse tensions on Russia’s southern flank in an effort to persuade the Russian government that it poses no threat to Russia’s strategic interests in the region. For Russia, relations with Iran offer an important new market for Russia’s strategic goods and the prospect of better security in the Islamic south, an issue that took on added urgency after the first and second Chechen wars.  </Para><Para>The military  </Para><Para>The revolution and the eight-year war with Iraq substantially weakened Iran’s military capability. Many senior officers were purged following the revolution, and a great deal of Iran’s weapons and equipment were destroyed during the war with Iraq. Modernisation efforts in recent years have focused on creating a leaner, more efficient military able to cope with simultaneous attacks on two borders. Iran has bought submarines and attack aircraft from the ex-Soviet republics and from North Korea and China, and has begun to manufacture its own military hardware, including field artillery, helicopters and battle tanks. It has also built its own medium-range missiles, which are believed to be propelled by rockets imported from North Korea. The most advanced missile Iran has deployed, the Shehab-III, has a range of around 2,000 km, and longer-range missiles are apparently under development.  </Para><Para>Iran’s armed forces are estimated to number some 540,000 active personnel, co-ordinated by a single high command, with a further 350,000 held in reserve. Ayatollah Khamenei is commander-in-chief of the armed forces. The 350,000-strong army is made up of about 130,000 regulars and 220,000 conscripts who serve for 21 months. It is divided into four armoured and six infantry divisions, two commando divisions and a special forces division. The navy numbers some 18,000, including 2,600 marines. Its equipment includes three Russian-manufactured “Kilo” class submarines and three frigates. The 52,000-strong air force, which in 1979 was well supplied with UK- and US-made aircraft, battles continuously against deteriorating equipment; only around half of its US-built F-4, F-5, F-14 and F-7 aircraft are now thought to be operational, although the purchase of MiG-29 fighters from Russia has partly alleviated shortages of top-line equipment.  </Para><Para>“Revolutionary” forces  </Para><Para>Government distrust of the army, which was used extensively by the shah to put down uprisings in 1978-79, led to the formation of the Pasdaran-e Inqilab (Revolutionary Guards) after the revolution. Numbering 120,000, the guards are responsible for internal security, ground attack, paratroops and marine duties. Lower ranks of the Pasdaran are believed to be divided in their political sympathies (with a significant number, for example, rumoured to have voted for Mr Khatami). However, Pasdaran officers are generally staunch conservatives, who have supported conservative allies in the judiciary and the bonyad and have become increasingly visible in non-military life in recent years. A sizeable number of the Abadgaran bloc, which prevailed in the 2004 Majlis elections, are former members of the Revolutionary Guard.  </Para><Para>The baseej (volunteers) is a people’s militia of largely untrained volunteers, who in theory make up part of the regular army. The 300,000-strong baseej came to prominence during the war with Iraq, when they took the brunt of the military’s losses by adopting “human wave” tactics to defend territory and attack Iraqi positions. Although the baseej remain a visible internal security force in the major cities, they do not currently play any role in military operations or manoeuvre.  </Para><Para display='asis'>Military forces, 2003
Regular forces  
Army           350,000
 Conscripts    220,000
Navy           18,000
Air force      52,000
Pasdaran        
Ground forces  100,000
Naval forces   20,000
Marines        5,000
Source: International Institute for Strategic Studies, The Military Balance 2002/03.
  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>Risk Briefing 07 Apr 2006 (T12:01), Part 10 of 11  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(C) 2006 The Economist Intelligence Unit Ltd.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>