<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="RSKW000020060404e24300008" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060403"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Israel risk: Security risk  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>COUNTRY BRIEFING  </Para><Para>FROM THE ECONOMIST INTELLIGENCE UNIT  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para display='asis'>RISK RATINGS       Current Current Previous Previous
                   Rating  Score   Rating   Score
Overall assessment B       31      B        31
Security risk      C       46      C        46
Note: E=most risky; 100=most risky.
  </Para><Para>SUMMARY  </Para><Para>Israeli-Palestinian unrest has diminished considerably but the security environment remains volatile, and will especially affect the tourism and construction sectors. The unresolved conflict with the Palestinians, Syria and Lebanon have led to attacks in Israel and on Jewish settlements, although these are at a lower level than in the past. Even if calm is mostly maintained and the peace process is restored, progress, particularly on substantive issues, will be slow. Israel remains vulnerable to attacks from Palestinian militant groups and the Lebanese Hizbollah. Nevertheless, Israel's military is by far the best-trained and equipped in the region, and the risk that a crossborder confrontation will broaden into a wider conflict is minimal. Israel will remain concerned about Iran's nuclear ambitions. Organised crime is a concern but is mostly limited to prostitution, drug and people-smuggling, and is not a threat to legitimate businesses, while policing of money-laundering, though an issue, is improving.  </Para><Para>SCENARIOS  </Para><Para>The Israeli-Palestinian conflict flares up as efforts to encourage adherence to peace or security initiatives fail (High Risk)  </Para><Para>Israel's security climate has improved considerably since unrest reached a peak in 2001-03, but there have been few substantive developments in peacemaking. The international roadmap to peace launched in June 2003 had serious deficiencies. It did not include specific details of a final settlement, and instead left such issues open to subsequent negotiations. Increased disaffection on both sides with continuing unrest raised hopes of relaunching peace initiatives in 2004-05. The agreement of a mutual ceasefire--which has mostly held, albeit with a few notable flare-ups--and other confidence-building measures in early February 2005 also increased optimism regarding a return to negotiations as did the successful completion of Israel’s disengagement from the Gaza Strip and four small settlements in the West Bank. But a restarting of the bilateral peace process is unlikely to begin until after Israel has held legislative elections in March 2006. Moreover, with Mr Sharon incapacitated by a stroke, his successor, Ehud Olmert, has to work harder to prove his security credentials to the Israeli public before proceeding with any peace initiatives. Even if a peace process is restored, the commitment on both sides may prove shaky at best. Militant groups may carry out violent attacks against Israeli targets, while Israel will resort to a sustained policy of attacking alleged militants if it feels the PA lacks control of security forces. Although there was broad public support in Israel for disengagement, it caused major political party ruptures. Even if peacemaking initiatives are restored, businesses should be aware that radical groups (on both sides) could carry out attacks in a bid to derail these efforts. Although foreign businesses are unlikely to be targeted specifically, they should maintain a high level of security at their places of business--as is common practice among local firms.  </Para><Para>Palestinian militants begin to target foreign businesses (Low Risk)  </Para><Para>Even if unrest resumes, attacks by Palestinian militant groups are unlikely to single out foreign businesses, although US officials travelling in the Gaza Strip in 2003 were targeted and killed and there have been several (relatively brief and peacefully resolved) kidnappings of foreign aid personnel since then. Assaults will focus on Israeli military personnel and installations. However, Israeli civilians in Jewish settlements in the Palestinian Territories and in Israeli towns could also be targeted, as may Israeli targets overseas by militants sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. Businesses operating in joint ventures between Israel and either Egypt or Jordan could be singled out for attack and should proceed with extra caution, but these incidents are likely to be rare. Foreign businesses, particularly in leisure and commerce, should ensure that they employ security personnel to screen persons entering their premises--a widespread practice among local businesses--and should avoid activity in or around Jewish settlements in the Palestinian Territories.  </Para><Para>Palestinian-Israeli conflict spills over into a broader regional conflict (Moderate Risk)  </Para><Para>Tensions on the Israeli-Syrian border occasionally spill over into military confrontation. While incidents such as the confrontation in mid-November 2005--the most serious since Israel's withdrawal from southern Lebanon in 2000--and further sporadic border clashes between Israeli forces and Hizbullah are likely to continue, they are unlikely to lead to open warfare. However, there is uncertainty regarding Hizbullah's future direction following the withdrawal from Lebanon of Syria--a key backer--in early 2005. Israel is also concerned over possible Syrian or Hizbullah support for Palestinian militant groups. Israel will continue to improve relations with some Arab states if there is some progress on resolving substantive issues with the Palestinians. Jordan and Egypt, the only two Arab states to have signed peace treaties with Israel, both recently returned their ambassadors to Israel following a four-year gap. Israel has also held tentative discussions with several Muslim (Pakistan) and Arab states (Morocco, Tunisia, Qatar and Bahrain), regarding establishing low-level trade and diplomatic ties. Israel would be able to cope with a conventional attack from an Arab state, given its superior military capability and robust anti-missile defence systems. However, it would find a prolonged guerrilla conflict (as occurred in southern Lebanon) or non-conventional attacks or threats (biological, chemical or nuclear) more difficult to handle. Foreign businesses are advised to follow the latest advice, including Israeli directives, in safeguarding against and coping with a conventional or other attack and to prepare evacuation procedures for foreign staff, particularly those based in Tel Aviv and the centre of the country.  </Para><Para>BACKGROUND  </Para><Para>(Background material is updated twice yearly. Last update: June 2nd, 2005)  </Para><Para>Armed Conflict  </Para><Para>Despite the formal declaration of an end to the conflict with the Palestinians and the expression of warmer ties at the Sharm al-Sheikh summit, there still have been some flare-ups of violence. A bomb at the Karni crossing into the Gaza Strip killed six in mid-January 2005. A Palestinian militant also blew himself up outside a Tel Aviv night-club on February 25th 2005, killing five civilians. This was the first successful suicide bombing in Israel in some four months. In an effort to prevent an escalation of unrest, Israeli forces did not respond directly to the attack, although a Palestinian alleged to have played a central role in the bombing was killed two weeks later in an attempt to capture him by the IDF. The firing by Palestinian militants of Qassam rockets from the northern strip to nearby Israeli towns has also continued, albeit on a far more sporadic basis than in 2004.  </Para><Para>The Palestinian Authority (PA) has so far attempted to co-opt rather than confront politically strong militant groups such as Hamas, although it has pledged to crack down on security. However, the general level of violence has been far more muted than that seen in 2004, when the unrest had already moderated from the 2001-02 peak. Moreover, in late March, at a summit hosted by Egypt, Palestinian officials met with the representatives of 13 Palestinian factions, many of which had not signed on to the ceasefire agreed between Mahmoud Abbas and Ariel Sharon in February 2005. Mr Abbas was able to win the backing of these groups to a temporary ceasefire until the end of 2005, dependent on Israel maintaining its Sharm al-Sheikh commitments. However, groups such as Hamas ruled out a more long-term truce at this stage.  </Para><Para>Unrest/Demonstrations  </Para><Para>Although Israel has been a parliamentary democracy since 1948, Arab citizens of Israel were for many years denied their full civil rights. This group continues to suffer from a lack of government resources, relative poverty compared with their Jewish counterparts, and a lack of opportunities stemming in large part from the fact that most Arabs do not serve in the army (Druze and some Bedouin serve) as well as from the perception among many Jewish Israelis that Arab Israelis have divided loyalties. The outbreak of Israeli-Palestinian unrest has increased Arab Israelis’ hostility towards the government. The Arab Israeli community is too divided and weak to pose a consistent threat to Israel’s political and economic fabric, but the involvement of a very small number of Arab Israelis in aiding Palestinian attacks against Israeli targets is a worry to Israel’s defence establishment. Within the Jewish community, there are also deep divisions over the issue of religion in the state, the peace process, and over the relative prosperity of the Ashkenazi Jewish community compared with Mizrahi Jews. Ultra-orthodox religious extremists have been blamed for attacks on properties and individuals that they deem unacceptable. However, these divisions in Israeli society have rarely manifested themselves in terms of opposition to or attacks on foreign businesses.  </Para><Para>Crime  </Para><Para>Economic prosperity and the welfare state have helped ensure that Israel has a relatively modest crime rate. However, Israel does have problems with organised crime in some areas. Car theft from Israel to the Palestinian Territories, operated by both Palestinian and Israeli criminal gangs, became a serious problem in the 1990s. However, the outbreak of Palestinian unrest in 2000 precipitated closures between Israel and the Territories, leading to a fall in the incidence of these crimes. With the economy weak in 2001-03, property-related crime among Israelis increased, but it has begun to decline in 2004 as the economy has started to recover. Israel has a rigorous criminal justice system, but in the past Jewish individuals who have perpetrated politically motivated attacks on Palestinians have received light--if any--sentences. There have been several incidents where foreign tourists have been killed or injured as a result of Israeli-Palestinian unrest, but foreigners are unlikely to be singled out, with the very occasional exception of identifiable Jewish tourists.  </Para><Para>Organised Crime  </Para><Para>Organised crime poses a threat in some industries in Israel. The wave of immigration in the early 1990s from the former Soviet Union also brought with it an increase in organised crimes centred around prostitution and money-laundering. Israeli crime gangs have also reportedly been involved in the smuggling of illegal immigrants to Europe as well as in the illegal drug trade. Israel’s position as a global centre for the diamond industry also makes it vulnerable to illicit sales of the precious mineral. In 2002 the Israeli government set up a body empowered to combat money-laundering, and in June that year the OECD’s Financial Action Task Force (FATF)--an international monitoring body--removed Israel from its list of states blacklisted for being too lenient with regards to money-laundering activities. Israel is often slow, or even fails, to extradite its citizens to face criminal charges, even to those countries with which it has extradition agreements.  </Para><Para>Kidnapping and Extortion  </Para><Para>Kidnapping and extortion of foreign executives is virtually unheard of, with criminal gangs limiting their attacks to their own circles.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>Risk Briefing 03 Apr 2006 (T12:05), Part 8 of 11  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(C) 2006 The Economist Intelligence Unit Ltd.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>