<DistDoc doctype="article" distdocver="05.1" an="RSKW000020060404e24300007" action="add" dist=""><DATE value="20060403"/>

<Article markup='pp0' lang='en' index='field'><HandL fid='hlp'><Title fid='hl'><Headline fid='hd'><Para lang='en'>Israel risk: Political stability risk  </Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid='lp'><Para>COUNTRY BRIEFING  </Para><Para>FROM THE ECONOMIST INTELLIGENCE UNIT  </Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid='td'><Para display='asis'>RISK RATINGS             Current Current Previous Previous
                         Rating  Score   Rating   Score
Overall assessment       B       31      B        31
Political stability risk C       50      C        50
Note: E=most risky; 100=most risky.
  </Para><Para>SUMMARY  </Para><Para>The country's volatile geopolitical environment, coupled with wide socio-economic differences, make for a fractious political scene. Moreover, the electoral system helps to reinforce religious, ethnic and other tensions. Differences in ideology over the country's security and the peace process are also common. Although Prime Minister Ariel Sharon had broad public support for his policies, managing the ideological divides within his coalition was more challenging. They eventually led to Labour's departure and the calling of elections for March 2006, from which the centrist Kadima party that Mr Sharon founded is likely to emerge victorious. Religious and socio-economic differences could manifest themselves in protests but serious violence is unlikely. Israel's Arab population, almost 20% of the total, is divided politically and has become more radicalised after the killing of 13 Israeli Arabs in demonstrations in September 2000. However, this minority is unlikely to pose a challenge to the political system.  </Para><Para>SCENARIOS  </Para><Para>The government coalition proves to be unstable (High Risk)  </Para><Para>Although Likud, the party of the prime minister, Ariel Sharon, won the largest number of seats in the January 2003 general election, Mr Sharon found it difficult to reconcile his government’s right-wing stance with broad national support for a withdrawal from some Palestinian territories. A change in the Labour leadership finally led to its departure from the coalition government (prompting elections in March 2006). This was followed by Mr Sharon's decision to leave the Likud to form a breakaway party--Kadima. Mr Sharon's policies remain popular, but with the prime minister incapacitated by a stroke, his party will now depend on his successor, Ehud Olmert, building on this support. Even if, as seems likely, Mr Olmert were to lead the next government, it will--as is always the case in Israel--be within a coalition. It could suffer from similar weaknesses, possibly collapsing when substantive “final status” issues return to the agenda and ideological differences become more apparent. However, mainstream secular political parties generally hold broadly similar views on the broad direction of economic policy, and while some may favour labour unions over private firms, and a greater role for the public sector, none is liable to impose measures that would specifically hinder the activities of foreign firms operating in Israel. Even so, businesses should be aware that many top positions in the country’s administration change when there is a change in government and keep abreast of such developments. However, Israel has stringent regulations regarding ties between business and political activity (although these have been known to have been violated on occasion), including a ban on foreign campaign financing, and firms should consult with their embassies or local legal representatives to find out about restrictions.  </Para><Para>Smaller political parties use their power to impose further restrictions on businesses (Moderate Risk)  </Para><Para>Reforms in effect since the 2003 vote restored the long-standing electoral system whereby the head of the largest party is called on to form the government. The system is intended to strengthen the hand of the larger parties, but numerous small parties were elected to the Knesset in the 2003 general election, and they still wield power disproportionate to their size. Although for the 2006 election there has been a further small increase in the vote threshold for parliamentary representation to 2%, it remains extremely low by international standards. The leader of the largest party following the general election will almost certainly have to rely on at least one large coalition partner and possibly some smaller groups to form his new coalition. The government will still be vulnerable to pressure from interest groups to meet their demands in return for backing government policies. This is particularly true of religious parties, which will continue to oppose measures that liberalise business activity on the Jewish Sabbath (Saturday) or otherwise threaten the religious status quo. Given the need for the next government to make progress on other sensitive matters such as national security, it is likely to give in on some of these issues and to boost spending on projects favoured by these groups in order to attract religious parties into government. Firms hoping to set up business in the leisure, transport and commerce sectors should be aware of these strictures. Hostility to commercial activity on the Sabbath varies across districts and even neighbourhoods within cities; businesses should study local conditions carefully before establishing operations.  </Para><Para>BACKGROUND  </Para><Para>(Background material is updated twice yearly. Last update: June 2nd, 2005)  </Para><Para>Political Forces  </Para><Para>Current government  </Para><Para>The position of the prime minister, Ariel Sharon, looks more secure in the short term at least as he has overcome several serious political hurdles and as the security situation has improved following progress in restoring Palestinian-Israeli dialogue after four years of unrest. Nevertheless, the political climate remains fragile. Mr Sharon lost all his original coalition partners over the course of 2004, with the secularist Shinui (15 seats) the last to depart in November 2004. This left his coalition dependent solely on the 40 Knesset (parliament) members of his right-wing Likud party in the 120-member parliament, and on the tacit outside support of the centre-left Labour (19 seats), who backed the prime minister in a bid to ensure that diplomatic initiatives relating to the Palestinian-Israeli conflict could progress.  </Para><Para>However, by early January 2005 Mr Sharon had managed to bring Labour (the second-largest party in the Knesset) and the ultra-orthodox United Torah Judaism (UTJ; which has five seats) into a new coalition to supplement Likud. This gives him a 64-member coalition, which in theory should make his position more secure. However, in the Knesset vote on the approval of the new government on January 10th, 13 of Mr Sharon’s own Likud party members voted against the government in protest at his disengagement plan for the Gaza Strip and a few settlements in the northern West Bank. This meant that the new government scraped through on a vote of 58 to 56 in the Knesset. The uncertain voting behaviour of these 13 “rebels” has effectively turned the new government into a minority one, with only 51 reliable votes. This situation has forced Mr Sharon to seek support from outside his government for key legislation (such as on the disengagement or the 2005 budget) to prevent the coalition from collapsing. The political climate therefore remains extremely uncertain, which could in turn threaten progress on both economic and security issues.  </Para><Para>Labour and the left  </Para><Para>The Labour Party has traditionally favoured territorial concessions on the areas occupied by Israel in 1967. However, the ongoing failure in the peace process, the violent Palestinian uprising and the lack of strong charismatic leadership since the death of Yitzhak Rabin has blurred the party’s official position on the Middle East peace process and the latter's appeal to a wider public. A failed attempt to pull the party to the left in the 2003 election by the then leader, Amram Mitzna, resulted in Labour recording its biggest defeat since the foundation of the state, although it is still the second-largest party in the Knesset. On issues of state and religion, Labour has often favoured a more secularist policy stance than Likud, primarily owing to its Ashkenazi secular middle class constituency, although the realities of coalition politics has meant that it has often had to acquiesce to the demands of religious parties.  </Para><Para>On the left of the political spectrum, Meretz, whose ideological foundation is in the old left-wing party, Mapam, and in the human rights movement, joined forces with Shahar, created by former Labour politicians, to form a social democratic party, Yahad, in March 2004. It supports the creation of a Palestinian state and, in domestic affairs, advocates the separation of state and religion. On economic and social issues it supports the existence of a welfare state along with an open economic system.  </Para><Para>The ultra-orthodox and religious parties  </Para><Para>The two ultra-religious parties, Shas and United Torah Judaism (UTJ), are both narrow-interest parties. Although Shas was the third most powerful force in Israeli politics for over a decade, it has lost that place to Shinui since the 2003 election. It represents a low-income, traditional Sephardic population who feel alienated from state resources. The UTJ, while taking a generally “hawkish” line over the Palestinians Territories, acts mainly to promote the interests of its constituency--the ultra-orthodox--notably over housing and welfare issues. During the course of the latest Israeli-Palestinian unrest, the NRP, Shas and the UTJ have often banded together in the Knesset to make a stand on civil and economic issues that affect its voters. However, the exclusion of the ultra-orthodox parties from the coalition seriously undermines their ability to hold the balance of power in the stalemate between the left and the right.  </Para><Para>Arab parties  </Para><Para>Many of the secular Jewish parties (Labour, Likud and Meretz) have Arab voters and even Knesset members, but there are several parties that more specifically cater to this constituency, which comprises just under 20% of the electorate. Arab voters are represented in the Knesset by three parties, which are unable to overcome their differences and unite as one bloc. These parties are the recently formed Balad and Ta’al, and the United Arab List, which includes MKs from the Islamic Movement. Arabs also feature prominently in the communist Hadash party. The deaths of 13 Arab demonstrators in violent clashes with the Israeli police in October 2000, and the May 2003 arrest of 15 Islamic leaders have alienated the Arab population from the Israeli establishment and have motivated pro-Palestinian activity among their Knesset representatives.  </Para><Para>Main political figures  </Para><Para>Ariel Sharon: Elected to the post of prime minister in February 2001 on a pledge of greater security, Ariel Sharon was re-elected following the January 2003 general election, as the Likud emerged as the largest party in the Knesset (parliament). Although his reputation as Likud’s most prominent “hawk” comes from his past objection to all peace initiatives, recent public statements in favour of an independent Palestinian state and his proposals for a unilateral Israeli redeployment from the Gaza Strip have put him towards the left of his party (albeit in line with broader public sentiment), although his commitment to a viable Palestinian state remains in some doubt. Mr Sharon took over leadership of the Likud in June 1999, following the resignation of Binyamin Netanyahu, and rehabilitated the party. Mr Sharon has served in several ministries and was foreign minister and defence minister during the Lebanon war. He is considered a brilliant military strategist, although his extreme actions during the 1982 war left him in the political wilderness for some years as well as making him extremely unpopular in the Arab world.  </Para><Para>Binyamin Netanyahu: The current finance minister, Binyamin Netanyahu resigned as Likud party head in 1999 after his electoral defeat by the then Labour leader Ehud Barak. A former prime minister and foreign minister, Mr Netanyahu is the Likud’s most prominent party member and the top contender to inherit the Likud’s leadership. A gifted orator, Mr Netanyahu has strong free-market beliefs, and has become an ardent hawk on the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. As finance minister he has been at the forefront of pushing through major economic reforms. Mr Netanyahu has recently voiced strong opposition to Palestinian statehood and has been reluctant to quell his distaste for Mr Sharon's Gaza Strip plan. However, he has more recently avoided making comments that directly oppose Mr Sharon’s proposals, aware that these are popular with the wider electorate, and has instead focused on pushing for economic reforms.  </Para><Para>Shimon Peres: Has remained at the centre of political life since the mid-1970s, having been part of the defence and the political establishment since the foundation of the state. Mr Peres has been behind most of the peace initiatives of the last decade and has been awarded the Nobel peace prize. He has served in all the major government posts, including two stints as prime minister, in a national unity government in 1984-86 and after the assassination of his predecessor, Yitzhak Rabin, but has consistently failed to win elections to the premiership and was defeated in a Knesset vote for the presidency in 2000. He took over the leadership of the Labour Party temporarily in February 2001 after Ehud Barak stepped down, but was replaced by Binyamin Ben-Eliezer after the party held primaries later in the year. Following the resignation of Amram Mitzna in May 2003, Mr Peres once again took over as temporary party head.  </Para><Para>Ehud Olmert: Minister of industry and trade, and deputy prime minister. The former mayor of Jerusalem, Mr Olmert is considered to be a contender to lead Likud after Mr Sharon retires. He has been one of Mr Sharon's strongest backers in the coalition. He is considered to be on the moderate wing of his party.  </Para><Para>The army: The Israel Defence Force (IDF) has a long tradition of remaining outside the political arena and being subject to the authority of the government of the day. Nevertheless, numerous senior military officers have carved out significant political careers after leaving the IDF, including Moshe Dayan, Mr Rabin, Mr Barak, current defence minister Shaul Mofaz (who took this post just a few months after retiring as chief of staff of the IDF) and Mr Sharon. However, the recent failures of Mr Barak and Mr Mitzna and several other high-ranking officers in their political careers appears to suggest that voters have become wary of electing military figures without political experience to senior political positions.  </Para><Para>Political Development  </Para><Para>The immigration of hundreds of thousands of Jews from the former Soviet Union from the beginning of the 1990s introduced a new force into Israeli politics. The considerable immigrant vote is generally liberal on domestic affairs but less compromising on security matters. Since the 1992 elections new immigrant voters have switched allegiance from the Likud to Labour and back. A more recent development is the emergence of the ultra-secular Shinui party as the third largest political party. The secular-religious relationship has always been delicate in Israel, but with the impasse in the peace process, the growing focus on domestic policy and the troublesome economy, tensions have increased over this issue. Many ultra-orthodox Jews refuse to recognise the existence of the Israeli state, and have practically withdrawn from the wider Israeli society while many others refuse to serve in the Israeli army (which is conscription based). This in turn leads to their exclusion from the labour market, which, coupled with their relative poverty and large families, means that they are heavily dependent on state handouts. However, in large part owing to Israel’s political system of proportional representation, ultra-orthodox political parties are able to wield significant political influence. This, together with the fact that secular Israelis and traditional religious Zionists--such as those that support the NRP--bear the brunt of military service and also pay more in taxes, has created a serious divide between secular and religious Jews. As the political stalemate grew, the religious parties successfully utilised the fractious political system to retain control over the balance of power in a succession of both left- and right-wing governments.  </Para><Para>The most successful of these religious parties has been Shas, but the party has weakened recently as the narrow political focus of religious parties and their financial demands on governments has led to a backlash, most obviously when Shinui saw its Knesset representation leap from six to 15 seats in the 2003 election. Participating in government for the first time, Shinui is a centrist party on security issues and advocates economic liberalisation and the separation of state and religion. Shinui’s voters are mostly middle and upper-middle class Ashkenazi (European) Jews (traditionally Labour voters). However, in the past centrist parties have performed strongly in an election and served in government only to disappear by the time of the next election.  </Para><Para display='asis'>Election results
(No. of seats in the Knesset)
                         1984  1988  1992  1996  1999   2003
Labour                   44    39    44    34    26 (a) 19 (a)
Likud (b)                41    40    32    32    19     38
Shas                     4     6     6     10    17     11
Meretz (c)               -     -     12    9     10     6
Centre Party             - (d) - (d) - (d) - (d) 6      - (d)
Shinui (d)               3     2     -     -     6      15
National Union           -     -     -     -     -      7 (f)
Yisrael Ba’Aliya         - (d) - (d) - (d) 7     6      2 (g)
National Religious Party 4     5     6     9     5      6
United Torah Judaism     2     5     4     4     5      5
United Arab List         - (d) 1     2     4     5      2
Hadash (h)               4     4     3     5     3      3
Am Ehad (a)              - (d) - (d) - (d) - (d) 2      3
Tsomet                   - (d) 2     8     - (I) -      - (d)
Moledet                  - (d) 2     3     2     -      - (d)
CRM (e)                  3     5     -     -     -      -
Others                   15    9     -     4     10     3
Total                    120   120   120   120   120    120
(a) One Israel alliance originally comprising Labour, Gesher and Meimad but only Labour and Meimad in 2003 election. Am Ehad scheduled to join One Israel alliance from October 2004. (b) Includes Tsomet and Gesher since the 1996 election. (c) Meretz merged with Shahar, a new left-wing party, to form Yahad in March 2004. (d) Did not contest election. Having joined with other parties to form the electoral bloc, Meretz, in 1992, Shinui left to stand alone in the 2003 Knesset elections. (e) The Civil Rights Movement (CRM) joined forces with Mapam, which had fought the 1981 and 1984 elections in conjunction with Labour, and with Shinui to form Meretz in 1992; Shinui subsequently left the federation in 1999. (f) Union of ultra right-wing parties including immigrant party Yisrael Beiteinu. (g) Merged with Likud after the 2003 general election. (h) The DFPE (Democratic Front for Peace and Equality) and the Israel Communist Party (HADASH in Hebrew). HADASH has historically been a Jewish-Arab movement, although it is now a predominantly Arab party.  (i) Tsomet fought 1996 election in alliance with Likud and Gesher.
Source: Official Knesset publications.
  </Para><Para>The assassination of Yitzhak Rabin, a centrist Labour prime minister, by an ultra-nationalist Israeli Jew in November 1995 highlighted the political tensions generated by the peace process in Israel. Left-right rivalry on the Arab-Israeli question predates the foundation of the state. Labour (left) and Likud (right) are the two main parties representing this ideological divide. The differences between the two parties on economic issues are minor, with both cautiously espousing (if not always implementing) generally liberal economic policies, although in the past Labour pursued centrally planned economic policies.  </Para><Para>However, a new electoral system inaugurated in 1996 brought about another result: the fragmentation of Israeli politics. The two major parties, Likud and Labour, which had previously tended to secure at least 80 seats between them, were able to muster only 66 seats in the 1996 election. This trend was intensified in 1999, when Likud and One Israel (Labour and its electoral bloc) managed to win only 19 and 26 seats respectively. By contrast, social issue parties increased their seat total from 22 in 1992 to 47 seats in 1999. In 2001 the Knesset approved a bill to reinstate the previous voting system, whereby the leader of the largest party or voting bloc is called on to form a government. Implemented in the 2003 election, the reversion to the old voting system stemmed the fragmentation of the political landscape but did not reverse it markedly: Labour and Likud secured 59 seats between them, while the smaller parties’ representation fell to 39 seats from 47 seats in the previous Knesset. Although these figures suggest that some of the electorate is returning to its pre-1996 voting patterns, the days of single-party predominance in the Knesset appear to be over. The two parties that have long been dominant are likely to continue to struggle to establish durable coalitions given the increased representation of religious, ultra-nationalist and other single- or narrow-issue parties. The Knesset has also voted in legislation raising the threshold for a party to gain a parliamentary seat from 1.5% of the vote--one of the lowest in the world--to a still low 2.5%, effective from the next general election.  </Para><Para>Important recent events  </Para><Para>November 1995: The assassination of the prime minister, Yitzhak Rabin, by a right-wing religious nationalist Israeli marks the end of a period where the Arab-Israeli conflict seems closer to a solution following the signing of the Oslo Accord with the Palestinians in 1993, and the peace agreement with Jordan in 1994.  </Para><Para>May 1999: Early elections lead to a sweeping victory for the One Israel alliance under the directly elected Labour leader, Ehud Barak, whose stance vis-a-vis peace negotiations is more flexible than Binyamin Netanyahu’s Likud-led government, paving the way for the start of final status peace negotiations.  </Para><Para>May 2000: Israel withdraws from southern Lebanon after 22 years of occupation.  </Para><Para>July 2000: Mr Barak and the Palestinian Authority (PA) chairman, Yasser Arafat, meet at Camp David in the US to finalise a final Israeli-Palestinian peace agreement. Talks reach an impasse despite the direct role of the US president, Bill Clinton, and the reaching of an informal basis for future political agreements.  </Para><Para>September 29th 2000: Violent clashes erupt between Israeli forces and Palestinians and eventually evolve into a second Palestinian intifada (uprising), frustrating hopes that informal progress at the Camp David talks could pave the way for a full settlement.  </Para><Para>December 2000-January 2001: Israeli-Palestinian talks at Taba in Egypt suggest the basis for an agreement but fail to prevent escalating violence.  </Para><Para>February 2001: Likud leader, Ariel Sharon, is elected in special prime ministerial-only election. A national unity government is formed.  </Para><Para>March-April 2002: Following a wave of deadly attacks perpetrated by Palestinian groups against Israeli citizens, the Israeli army invades Palestinian cities in an effort to "root out terrorist infrastructure”. Israeli forces attack Palestinian targets and enter Palestinian towns.  </Para><Para>June-July 2002: Israel begins to construct a security fence that initially runs close to, but over, its pre-1967 borders, intended to draw in many Jewish settlements and potentially to extend to parts of the Jordan Valley.  </Para><Para>October-November 2002: Labour withdraws from the coalition government, leaving Mr Sharon with a minority government. He calls early elections after refusing to meet demands set by nationalist parties for entering the government.  </Para><Para>January 28th 2003: General elections are held. Mr Sharon’s Likud wins 38 seats in the 120-member Knesset, up from 19. Labour plummets to its lowest ever representation, with a mere 19 seats. The ultra-secular Shinui party strengthens while the orthodox Shas loses seats.  </Para><Para>February 2003: Mr Sharon’s new government comprising Likud, Shinui, National Union and the National Religious Party is sworn in.  </Para><Para>April-May 2003: With the conclusion of the US-led war in Iraq, a new government in Israel and a Palestinian prime minister in place, the US government decides to publish the “road map” to peace and to become more directly involved in the peace process.  </Para><Para>June-August 2003: Road map launched at Aqaba summit. Violence continues, nevertheless, with a spate of attacks by Palestinian militant groups and harsh Israeli reprisals including “targeted assassinations”. Nevertheless, some radical Palestinian groups agree to a conditional ceasefire and Israel begins to dismantle illegal outposts and redeploy troops from some Palestinian areas. Ceasefire breaks down in mid-August.  </Para><Para>December 2003: Mr Sharon announces that Israel is to proceed with unilateral measures aimed at improving the country's security, starting with a withdrawal of forces and Jewish settlers from the Gaza Strip.  </Para><Para>March-April 2004: Israel assassinates Sheikh Ahmed Yassin, the leader of the Islamist militant group, Hamas, and several weeks later kills his successor, Abdelaziz Al Rantissi. Mr Sharon meets with the US president, George W Bush, in the US to gain approval for disengagement proposals and receives backing for the retention of some settlements in the West Bank and East Jerusalem as part of a peace agreement.  </Para><Para>May 2004: In a party referendum Likud members reject plans for a unilateral Israeli withdrawal from the Gaza Strip and a small number of settlements in the northern West Bank. Israeli forces launch an offensive in Gaza.  </Para><Para>June 2004: Mr Sharon gets cabinet approval for a revised disengagement plan that would require a separate cabinet vote before each of four planned evacuation phases. However, ultra right-wing ministers depart from the coalition over the issue, leaving Mr Sharon with a minority government. The attorney-general drops bribery charges against the prime minister.  </Para><Para>July 2004: Around one-third of the planned 700-km West Bank "security fence" has been built. The International Court of Justice rules against Israel's construction of the barrier, but Israel does not accept that the issue is within the court's remit. Nevertheless, with the Israeli Supreme Court also ruling against parts of the barrier, the government has rerouted some of the barrier.  </Para><Para>International Relations and Defence  </Para><Para>The dominant factors shaping Israel’s foreign and defence policies have been the Arab-Israeli conflict and Israel’s alliance with the US. Upon declaring independence in 1948 Israel and neighbouring Arab states went to war. Subsequent hostilities occurred in 1956, 1967, 1973 and 1982. In 1991 Israel was attacked by Iraqi missiles during the Gulf war, in which it did not take part, but was not targeted by Iraq during the US war against the Iraqi leader, Saddam Hussein, in 2003. The Israeli-Palestinian conflict has dominated Israel’s relations with its neighbours. Until the 1990s one of the central tenets of Israeli diplomacy and domestic politics was its opposition to the idea of Palestinian political independence. The signing of the Oslo accords between Israel and the Palestine Liberation Organisation (PLO) in September 1993 signalled a new era in which the principle of partition, which was rejected by the Arabs when proposed by the UN in 1947, was accepted by the leadership of both peoples.  </Para><Para>Israeli-Palestinian relations improving but progress slow  </Para><Para>After a period of diminishing violence and with the death of the Palestinian leader, Yasser Arafat, hopes of a revival of the Palestinian-Israeli peace process have increased. Since the election of Mahmoud Abbas as PA president in January 2005, there have been further encouraging developments in Israeli–Palestinian relations. On February 9th 2005, at a summit hosted by the Egyptian president, Hosni Mubarak, in Sharm al-Sheikh, both Mr Sharon and Mr Abbas announced a cessation of hostilities between Israelis and Palestinians, paving the way for resumption of dialogue and co-operation between Israel and the PA. Moreover, they agreed to co-ordinate efforts on the disengagement from the Gaza Strip and the northern West Bank (a plan that had originally been unilateral in nature, rooted in Israeli disaffection with the Palestinian leadership’s failure to stop Palestinian attacks on Israelis). The Israelis and Palestinians also agreed to step up security co-ordination efforts that had already begun since Mr Abbas had assumed office.  </Para><Para>The Israeli government released 500 Palestinian security prisoners in February 2005 as part of its commitments at Sharm al-Sheikh to free 900 in total as a goodwill gesture to the Palestinians (the remainder are supposed to be released by May). This was the largest release of Palestinians prisoners by Israel in a decade. The Palestinians have demanded that Israel free many more of the estimated 8,000 Palestinians still held in Israeli jails. Many of those released were coming to the end of their sentence or had been imprisoned on charges not necessarily directly related to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. Nevertheless, Mr Sharon has hinted that Israel may be willing to free some Palestinian prisoners with “blood on their hands” at a future stage, a position he has previously rejected.  </Para><Para>Relations with neighbours start to improve  </Para><Para>Relations with Egypt and Jordan--the only two Arab states that have diplomatic ties with Israel--have warmed following the announcement of a cessation of hostilities between Israel and the PA. Both Egypt and Jordan have returned their ambassadors to Israel after more than four years without top level representation. Israel hopes to secure some regional co-operation in the implementation of its withdrawal from the Gaza Strip and parts of the West Bank. Egypt, which is keen to be seen as a regional mediator and political force, has been playing a particularly active role in mediating between the Israelis and Palestinians. Mr Mubarak met the Israeli defence minister, Mr Mofaz, on March 10th in Egypt to discuss the possibility of Israel evacuating the Philadelphi route along the Egyptian-Gazan border some time after the rest of the Israeli pull-out from the Gaza Strip is completed. Originally, Israel had planned to remain at Philadelphi even after the disengagement, in order to prevent arms smuggling from Egypt into the Gaza Strip. Israel will leave the Philadelphi route only if Egypt makes efforts to prevent smuggling. Egypt’s ability to do this will necessitate the stationing of troops along the border, which would require changing the terms of the 1979 Egyptian-Israeli peace agreement, a matter that has reportedly been discussed.  </Para><Para>An Arab League summit in March 2005 relaunched a 2002 Saudi peace initiative that had offered Israel normalised relations with Arab states in return for a withdrawal to its pre-1967 borders, but did not propose any new initiatives. Some members of the Israeli government have been more optimistic regarding an improvement of ties with regional states, with a Ministry of Foreign Affairs document suggesting in late February that ten Arab states would open embassies in Israel if and when the disengagement plan is completed.  </Para><Para>Tensions between Israel and Syria remain high. The mid-February 2005 assassination of the former prime minister of Lebanon, Rafiq al-Hariri, has generated uncertainty regarding Israel’s northern border. The killing prompted massive demonstrations in Lebanon protesting against Syria’s presence in the country. However, Syria’s subsequent decision to pull out its troops (almost completed as this report to print) from Lebanon, and Syria’s increased international isolation, should benefit Israel. Israel has also criticised Russian plans to sell missiles to Syria that would be capable of hitting targets in Israel.  </Para><Para>US involvement kept to the sidelines initially  </Para><Para>The hostile regional environment has compelled Israel to look further afield for political and military support. Since 1973 the US has filled this role, selling Israel advanced weapons systems and providing a diplomatic umbrella. The US continues to support peace negotiations between the Israelis and Palestinians. However, whereas in the past the US played an active role in such negotiations, the administration of the US president, George W Bush, appears to favour a less prominent position. Instead it has left the Palestinians and Israelis to negotiate without major US involvement, which would tie the US too closely to any failures and also make any agreement more vulnerable to criticism from Arab states that view the US as biased toward Israel. The US has allowed Egypt to take the diplomatic lead in mediation efforts while pledging logistical support for implementing agreements. The US has appointed a new envoy to the region, William Ward, specifically with a fairly modest remit as “security co-ordinator” to help reform the PA security apparatus.  </Para><Para>The US has also been a source of economic and military aid. Since 1985 this has taken the form of an annual grant of US$3bn, of which US$1.8bn is military aid spent primarily on American equipment. In 2003 the US agreed to extend Israel a further US$1bn in military aid that year to cover the costs of defending itself during the Gulf conflict. Although civilian aid from the US is being phased out over a ten-year period, military support will continue. Successive Israeli governments have made the link with the US a cornerstone of their policies. Israel is wary of any diplomatic role for the EU, and even more so for the UN, as their policies are perceived by Israelis to be more sympathetic to the Palestinian plight. Nevertheless, since the Palestinian uprising began in September 2000, the US, the EU, Russia and the UN (both individually and, since 2002, collectively as the four members of the Middle East "Quartet"), along with Saudi Arabia and, to a lesser but still significant extent, Arab states such as Egypt and Jordan, have all attempted to provide diplomatic and practical solutions to the ongoing violence and to bring about a resumption of negotiations between Israel and the Palestinians.  </Para><Para>There has been some friction between the US and Israel over the latter’s plans to upgrade China’s unmanned aerial vehicles (UAV) fleet. In November 2004 the foreign minister, Mr Shalom, visited China to finalise the deal. Israel had sold UAVs to China in the mid-1990s, with the consent of the US. The upgrade deal was originally signed in 1999 but the Israeli government has come under increased US pressure to abandon the deal, which it views as detrimental to its interests in the Taiwan Straits. Israel is required to inform the US of any arms sales that may involve military technology potentially originating in the US (even if the overall product or service is Israeli). In 2000 Israel cancelled a US$2bn sale to China of four Phalcon airborne reconnaissance aircraft after the US warned that it would not approve the deal and would consider cutting back the transfer of military technology to Israel if the sale went through.  </Para><Para>Defence doctrine and the army  </Para><Para>To counter the threat that it believes it faces from its neighbours, Israel has built up a strong military capability, based on conscription and a system of annual reserve duty. Of the IDF’s estimated serving strength of 167,600 in 2003, 107,500 were conscripts. Terms of service are 48 months for officers, 36 months for servicemen and 24 months for women. After military service is completed, male conscripts are required to serve one month a year until they reach 41, although this can be extended to 54 for certain specialists. For women, though service is also compulsory, fewer serve and the term of service usually ends after 24 months, except for those with specialist skills. The IDF uses a combination of Western and Israeli-produced materiel. Israel is believed to have had a nuclear capability for several decades, with up to 200 warheads, but the government and military have refused to either confirm or deny whether they possess a nuclear weapons capability.  </Para><Para display='asis'>Total armed forces, 2003
(mid-year)
Active forces       167,600
 Army               125,000
 Navy               7,600
 Air force          35,000
Reserve forces      358,000
Paramilitary forces 8,050
 Border police      8,000
 Coastguard patrol  50
Source: International Institute for Strategic Studies, The Military Balance 2003/04.
  </Para><Para>Israeli defence doctrine demands that the regular army be capable of absorbing a first strike by Arab forces to give time to mobilise reserves and push fighting into enemy territory. The concept has generally worked well, especially during the surprise attack that began the October war of 1973, although losses incurred during that war shattered a myth of invincibility generated by previous victories. Moreover, the IDF’s failure to reach its objectives in the 1982 Lebanon war, the duration of the two Palestinian intifadas (uprisings) and its withdrawal from southern Lebanon have all shown the limits of Israel’s military supremacy. Some of the Israeli army’s tactics during the unrest have led some IDF reserve officers to refuse to serve in the Palestinian Territories, sparking a military and public debate, but it has not led to widespread refusal to serve and the military has sufficient resources to pursue its current strategy. In March 2002 the army called up more than 20,000 reservists, the largest call-up since the Lebanon war, embarking on a military campaign that lay siege to the Palestinian Territories for several weeks. Another call-up took place in early 2003 in preparation for the possible fallout from war in Iraq.  </Para></TailParas><Byline index='field' fid='by'></Byline><Credit index='field' fid='cr'></Credit><Contact index='field' fid='ct'></Contact><Notes index='field' fid='rf'>Risk Briefing 03 Apr 2006 (T12:05), Part 7 of 11  </Notes><Art index='field' fid='art'></Art><Copyright index='field' fid='cy'>(C) 2006 The Economist Intelligence Unit Ltd.  </Copyright></Article></DistDoc>